<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Respublica Anglicana or The historie of the Parliament in their late proceedings Wherein the Parliament and Army are vindicated from the calumnies cast upon them in that libellous History of independency, and the falshoods, follies, raylings, impieties, and blasphemies, in that libell detected. The necessity and lawfullnesse of secluding the Members, laying aside the King, and House of Lords, is demonstrated. The lawfullnesse of the present power is proved, and the just and necessary grounds of the Armies march into Scotland are represented. Published for publicke satisfaction. The author G:W</title>
            <author>G. W.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96721</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W30A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E780_25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204087</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895812</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895812</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153720</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96721)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153720)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2375:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Respublica Anglicana or The historie of the Parliament in their late proceedings Wherein the Parliament and Army are vindicated from the calumnies cast upon them in that libellous History of independency, and the falshoods, follies, raylings, impieties, and blasphemies, in that libell detected. The necessity and lawfullnesse of secluding the Members, laying aside the King, and House of Lords, is demonstrated. The lawfullnesse of the present power is proved, and the just and necessary grounds of the Armies march into Scotland are represented. Published for publicke satisfaction. The author G:W</title>
                  <author>G. W.</author>
                  <author>Wither, George, 1588-1667, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 47, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by F. Leach, for George Thompson, dwelling at the sign of the White horse in Chancery-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to George Wither.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Walker, Clement.  The history of independency.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octo: 28".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Walker, Clement, 1595-1651. --  History of independency --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Expulsion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Political parties --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153720:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153720:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſpublica Anglicana</hi> OR THE HISTORIE OF THE PARLIAMENT In their late PROCEEDINGS, WHEREIN The Parliament and Army are vindicated from the calumnies caſt upon them in that libellous <hi>History of Independency,</hi> and the falſhoods, follies, raylings, impieties, and blaſphemies, in that Libell detected. The Neceſsity and lawfullneſſe of ſecluding the Members, laying aſide the King, and Houſe of Lords, is demonſtrated. The Lawfullneſſe of the preſent power is proved, and the juſt and neceſſary grounds of the Armies march into <hi>Scotland</hi> are repreſented. Publiſhed for publicke ſatisfaction. The Author <hi>G: W:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Lege, Perlege, &amp; Judica.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>F. Leach,</hi> for <hi>George Thompſon,</hi> dwelling at the ſign of the <hi>White horſe</hi> in Chancery-lane, 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:153720:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153720:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur Anceſtors would have rejoyced, might they have had but the libertie under their Kings to have folowed Truth at the heels, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger of their teeth, and have allowed a little Courtſhip in an Hiſtory to the preſent Prince for ſuch a favour; but now there is a ſort of men that nothing can content, unleſſe they may tread on truth's heels, and trample upon the preſent Governours; may and this ſort, ſhould another but term ſuch Kings Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, will flie in his face, whilſt themſelves will reproach the preſent Governors with Tyranny, and what not, becauſe they may not have licence to abuſe them, and Truth too, in their ſcurrilous Pamphlets: yet ſuch is the wiſdome of our times, that ſuch as theſe are the only vendible and cryed up writers, as if Liberty conſiſted in crying up Tyranny, and defaming thoſe that reſiſt it</p>
            <p>A ſecond ſort we have and they forſooth are all for the old way, all truths with theſe are Puritanical, Browniſticall, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſticall and Schiſmatical, which have not been entailed on by them their Grandſires: Religious and civill Government,
<pb facs="tcp:153720:3"/>muſt be a Gentleman of 3. deſcents, like a Knight of <hi>Malta,</hi> or it muſt not be admitted into their order, a right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tenent for ſuch who arrogate ſolely to themſelves the name Proteſtant. But ſay they, our fore-Fathers were wiſer than we, and we will follow them: we grant they were, for they embraced the Truth, and would not be ſcared by the bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear of Novelty; had they cryed out for the old way, how had theſe Youths ever have had any title to the Proteſtant Religion? the Maſſe was as ancient then, as the Common-Prayer Book now, and Priors, Abbots, and Monkes, as Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, Deanes, and Prebends, yet at the firſt dawning of truth they chaſed away thoſe Bats and Owles, and the new light ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, was embraced, not ſcorned; ſo that the dark ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of Ignorance and Superſtition vaniſhed, and the ferall Birds of Night were put to flight. Theſe were the worthy actions of our Proteſtant Anceſtors, whom theſe old-way-Men will needs imitate forſooth, by acting the quite contrary.</p>
            <p>A third ſort, are thoſe, who know not what they would have, they would have a King and they would not; they would have the Parliament prevaile, and yet the <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes muſt not be defeated; they will have the Privilege of Subjects, yet not perform the duties of Subjects; and receive protection, yet not return ſubjection: and is it not an hard caſe that their wiſhes and wills are not accompliſhed, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely contradictory may ſo eaſily be reconciled; and a great perſecution, that all men are not compelled to be of their minde?</p>
            <p>The laſt ſort are a Rabble which think no man can be reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, who is not of all Religions: with whom it is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtaniſme not to deny Chriſt, infidelity to beleeve the Scriptures, and he hath not the Spirit who excludes not the
<pb facs="tcp:153720:3"/>Holy Ghoſt, the Holy Trinity; with theſe it is ſin to abſtain ſro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne, and he the leaſt, who is the groſſeſt ſinner: but I abhor to mention theſe Champions of Hell, who war againſt Satan by being of his black Guard.</p>
            <p>And now, ſith every one will have his humour, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ridiculous, and wicked; I hope I may have the favour to enjoy my conſcience, though I differ from all or any of theſe crotchets.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe I conceive I am bound to praiſe God, and be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to Authority, that I may write truth, without fear of hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, pillory, or whip now, when I can remember, as young as I am, that to call a <hi>Spade</hi> a <hi>Spade,</hi> was counted no leſſe than Treaſon; as alſo that I abhor to play the knave to pleaſe fools, or to tickle their ears, by lyes bite, and railings ſcratch, all that are wiſer, honeſter, and more generous than ſuch dull ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malls: muſt I therefore be thought not worth the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding?</p>
            <p>Suppoſe I conceive I am bound to prefer naked truth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore error, though ſhe be brought in with the ſound of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Organs, or Scotch Bag-pipes, arrayed in a Surplice, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet, Cope and Miter, with tagg, ragge and bob-taile cringing and bowing to her; As alſo to make the Scriptures rather my Guide, than mens traditions and inventions, and to receive that as the good, and old way, which the <hi>ancient of dayes</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands me to walke in: muſt I therefore be no Proteſtant, but a Novelliſt?</p>
            <p>Suppoſe I conceive, that all powers that are are of God; that I ought to pray for Magiſtrates, that I may live a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and peaceable life under them; that I am bound to give ſubjection in all lawfull things, where I receive protection: muſt I therefore be a Traytor and ſeditious perſon?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153720:4"/>
            <p>Supoſe I conceive I cannot keep the Covenant, wherein I vowed <hi>to defend Religion and Liberty,</hi> by endeavouring to ſet up the Enemy of both, for my own private Faction or Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt; <hi>to endeavour to bring all Delinquents to consligne puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without reſpect of Perſons,</hi> by reſpecting the perſon of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man; <hi>to endeavour a Reformation according to the word of God,</hi> which is preach and baptize, not perfecute and force; that I cannot ſee any Juſtice in hanging up the Sword, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping as Sacred the Murderer; that I cannot attaine to comprehend that myſtery of maintaining Parliamentary pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege, by deſtroying, or ſuffering to be deſtroyed, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary power for ever: of keeping the Lawes; by making them act contrary to their end, the generall good; of crying out of perſecution, becauſe I may not force others to be of my opinion, though they equally deteſt with me all Hereſie and Blaſphemy: muſt I therefore be a Covenant Breaker, a Sectary, a favourer of Hereſie, and Blaſphemy? Sure ſuch Language as this, will never appear true Engliſh, though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt may alter the caſe in Scotch; but though it doe I care not, for I am an Engliſh man, and deſire to appear ſo, both in my language and intereſt: the Liberty I engaged for was that of my own Countrey, and in preſerving that, I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to daſh all Scotch and ſelf intereſt in peices, not that I abhor, or hate the perſons of the Scotch, but becauſe it is my duty to love and ſerve my Countrey.</p>
            <p>And truly ſo farre am I from hating that Nation, that I wiſh our Sectaries (as they term them) may be as diligent to inſtruct them in Liberty, as their Presbyterians will ſeeme forward in teaching us Religion: I would reward them good for evill, and though they doe ſtrive to pull us in, yet let us endeavour to help them out of ſlavery; it may
<pb facs="tcp:153720:4"/>be this alſo will be called Sectarian doctrine, but I care not: for though it may ſeem contrary to Scotch Declarations, yet it is conſonant to Heavens Ordinances, and I had rather obey God than men, than <hi>Scotch</hi> men, and ſhall account them no Chriſtians, who ſhall not judge it my duty to beleeve Him before a <hi>Scotch</hi> Committee of Eſtates or Kirk.</p>
            <p>To ſumme up all, I would have thee Reader know, <hi>That Fools and Knaves, whether</hi> Engliſh <hi>or</hi> Scotch, <hi>ſhall never fright nor juggle me out of chriſtianity and humanity, but that, by the aſſiſtance of God, I ſhall endeavour, as a Chriſtian, to make the Word; as a Man, Reaſon; and as an Engliſhman, the generall good of this Nation, the ground of all my actions: and in thus doing I value not thine, or any mans diſpleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell,</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:153720:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153720:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Reſpublica Anglicana,</hi> OR, The Hiſtory of the Parliament in their late proceedings, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Hiſtory of Independency,</hi> though it may appear to have been ſtiffled in the Birth, the greateſt part of the Firſt Impreſſion being ſuppreſt by publike Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and together with it's Author prohibited a publike walk; yet much of it in parcels having been before vented (the crafty Enemy skirmiſhing in ſmall parties before he would bring on his main body, &amp; by getting off without perſonall loſs growing more daring, but one ſubtiller than He owed Him a ſhame) and many of the laſt eſcaping the ſeizure, which were ſecretly diſperſt, and covertly re-printed by the Book-ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, of whom too many are more then enough prone to diſſerve the State, and theſe being greedily ſought, and at high prices bought, by that ſort of men who, <hi>audax omnium perpeti ruit in vetitum nefas,</hi> will hazard a Paradice to partake of forbidden fruit, it came in fine into moſt hands; thus being divulg'd, and not to be thought altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable, in regard of the politick compoſure, and crafty couch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it's Calumnies, backt much by the repute of the Author, lately a Member of the Houſe, and before a ſeeming Zealot in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Cauſe, as his fiery proſecution of Col. <hi>Nathaniel Fiennes,</hi> may perſwade many; I conceived it would be worth my labour, and not unbecomming my duty to diſcover the Impoſture, and vindicate the preſent Governours and Government from the falſe imputations caſt upon them by this, and other ſuch invectives belched out by him and others his accomplices, the <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levies</hi> Brethren in the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquity of this age. And though I may ſeem an unequall Match for ſuch a veterane, a Hoary Sophiſter; yet being aſſured that Truth will the more gloriouſly triumph in my weakneſs, I ſhall enter the Liſts, and in confidence of my cauſe, not only combate him, but dare the tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt of the Sons of <hi>Anak</hi> to the encounter, which ſhall endeavour to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153720:6"/>hinder our poſſeſſing the promiſed Land, the <hi>Canaan</hi> of Liberty; and what indeed ſhould I fear, when the deepeſt wounds I can receive will be but ſcarres of honour; and the worſt come to the worſt, I ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to have as reall a heart, though not ſo able a hand, as any, to the ſervice of my Country? But to leave off words and come to deeds, by which the controverſie muſt be decided, for a longer declining it may favour of fear. And now, though it be long ere I could abide to touch him, my Genius abhorring a Scold, I will uncaſe the Vrchin, that you may handle him without pricking your fingers.</p>
            <p>Of all things paſſion and affection ſhould not be diſcovered in an Hiſtorian, who muſt appear impartial in the manner, or elſe the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his writing will never gain belief: For Wiſe men diſcovering him to be a party, will not accept of his evidence in his own cauſe; the Author therefore was very indiſcreet to ſhew his Teeth ſo much, or if he could not bridle his paſſion, to ſtyle his Book an Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>A Politician knows, that by ſlightly commending he ſhal more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit his Adverſarie, than by openly reviling him: for ſeeming a friend, Men are apt to believe he adds when he diminiſhes, but appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a foe, they ſuſpect every thing to be detraction, and calumnie; Were I then but a Knave I would bate railing.</p>
            <p>Every one can ſtand on St. <hi>Georges</hi> guard, and ward a down right blow; and it is the firſt ſtep to ſafety to know ones enemy. <hi>Ioab</hi> ſpeaks peaceably to <hi>Abner,</hi> and pretends a kiſſe to <hi>Amaſa,</hi> when he intends to ſmite them under the fifth rib: Were I a Spider and ſuck'd poyſon where the Bee gathers Honie, were I an Atheiſt, and beleev'd not the Scriptures, yet could I have made more uſe of my Bible, than many now a dayes, who would be thought Chriſtians, and have learnt ſo much craft, that when I intended to Murther, it were the only ſure way under the vizor of a friend to mask my deſign.</p>
            <p>I muſt ingenuouſly confeſſe that I have alwayes ſmil'd at the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh bitterneſs of the Malignant party, and wondered that men who pretended to all the wit, to be the only learned and politique States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, could never diſcover their own folly, and diſcern how much their lying and railing diſadvantag'd themſelves, by making them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear rather Bedlams than Politicians, much leſſe Chriſtians: for who but wil judge he wants reaſon and truth, who patches up his diſcourſe with railing and falſhood?</p>
            <p>It ſeemes by the help of Iudge <hi>Ienkins,</hi> a notorious old ſcold, this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153720:6"/>quality of railing (heretofore by all Sages judged a fee fimple, nay ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſt) is turned into a tayl ſpecial, to a Malignant and his Heirs males, and ſo deſcends from <hi>Aulicus</hi> by <hi>Pragmaticus, Elencticus, &amp;c.</hi> to this Author, <hi>Theodorus Verax,</hi> in Engliſh <hi>Clement Walker.</hi> The Latine was falſe, I am therefore forced to mend it by truly conſtruing it. I hope he wil not take it as an injury that I name him, for he that ſeems ſo reſolute as to deſpiſe death, and what not, in his Cauſe, cannot with any gallantry deny to own it, when indeed he muſt whither he wil or no.</p>
            <p>This might ſeem ſtrange, nay almoſt incredible, were he not a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant, That <hi>Clement Walker,</hi> late a Member of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, an ancient, and ſo one might think a grave man, ſhould not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſgreſs the Rules of Hiſtory, Modeſty, Honeſty and Piety, but ſo affect Levity, and gibing, that rather than want He wil ſteal thread bare ſcurrility of thoſe beggarly Buffoons <hi>Prag.</hi> The <hi>Moon calf, &amp;c.</hi> to play with a mans Noſe, nay ſuch ſtuffe that he might wel ſuppoſe would be very nauſeous to any ingenuous ſtomack, having been ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vomited out before: O there is no Fool to an old one, nor none ſo bitter an Enemy to you, O Presbyters, as an old Malignant, who ſo deteſts you that he abhorres to follow an Author that is Claſſicall, for the very names ſake.</p>
            <p>Should I anſwer him at his own weapon, and fall foul upon his noſe, it would be but fair dealing, and he could not complain of hard or unjuſt uſage ſhould I mete the ſame meaſure to him that he hath done to others much more his betters; and it may be he will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of his own incivility to others, by ſeeing how ill it would becom me, ſhould I accoſt him with ſuch Complements.</p>
            <p>Truly were there hopes of this, I could be drawn to deny my ſelfe to recover him, and would ſtray to reduce this wanderer; as long as there is life there is hope: I beſeech you therefore to pardon if I ſhal a little digreſſe in hope that he is not incorrigible; and with your good leave, you ſhal ſee that if I would, I can be even with him; as for example.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I could tell you how it hath been obſerved that the Popes names and their natures ſeldome ſuited, as Pope <hi>Clem.</hi> here (who hath with Bel, Book, and Candle anathematiz'd the Parliament, Aſſembly, and Army, in this which may properly enough be termed his Bull by it's bellowing and goring) may as well be termed <hi>Boniface</hi> as <hi>Clement;</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:153720:7"/>yet ſhould you call him ſo, all that ever ſaw him may depoſe you abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him: for his face is as far from good as his Book, and both ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently enough proclaim him no true <hi>lement,</hi> in which are ſo to the life delineated an invective and ſpightful nature.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How he looks like the pourtraicture of Envy, or as the vulgar ſay, the picture of ill Lucke, Dame Nature having drawn as crooked Lines on his Front, as he hath on his Paper, and in both Volumes you may runne and read an <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> whoſe hand is againſt every one, a venemous little Animall, that waſts it's own Bowels to catch flies; for none elfe will be captivated.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How you might take him for a Reviver of the Sect of the Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks, a <hi>Diogenes</hi> in a Satten Doublet, but for his barking ſo againſt Tubs, and being ſo wretchedly infected with the itch of Covertouſneſs, as appears by his ſcratching now he dreams others have got more by ſitting in the Houſe than he hath done.</p>
            <p>I could alſo give you a deſcription of this little Chaos, this indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted ſpot, wherein lay hid — <hi>Diſcordia ſemina rerum,</hi> the ſeeds of Sedition, which have brought forth a very ful crop this year.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How Ingenuity is <hi>terraincognita,</hi> the unknown Land in the map of his face, which you would think all Sea by it's Billows, and yet no where deſcry <hi>Mare pacificum,</hi> the calm Sea, it is ſo rough with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall Tempeſts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How that if he ever had any ſign of modeſty it is now ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in the Pits of his Cheeks, which like the <hi>Curtian</hi> Gulfe could never be ſatisfied, until they had devoured the beſt thing in this little <hi>Babel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. How that the Remnant of Bloud taking the Alarm from the gnaſhing his Teeth, eſcaped into the tip of his noſe, which is turned a Red coat, and holds it lawful in ſpight of his Teeth or Tongue either, to maintain a Civil War, on the Ground of Selfe-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. How the leaſt read in Phyſiognomie may ſpell the ſtormes of his minde out of the Waves in his face, whoſe furrowed up and Downes make many a <hi>vacuum,</hi> that his out-ſide may be as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philoſophical as his in-ſide, an equal tranſgreſſor againſt God, and Nature.</p>
            <p n="5">5. How there is no more harmony without, than within him, and how had the ancient Egyptians been to figure out ſuch a Gipſie, the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153720:7"/>Bear and ragged ſtaffe had been the Hieroglyphick of his raging ſoule and rough caſt Body.</p>
            <p>Thus you and he may ſee, that I could, if I would play upon him without <hi>Prags.</hi> helpe; I deſire not to meddle with his Perſon, as knowing natural defects are not within a mans power to amend; yet it is a true ſaying, that we ſhould beware of thoſe whom God marks, and as true alſo, that many times a ragged ſoul wrinkles a ſmooth face: but it is needleſs to judge of his qualities by that, which will be beſt read in his book, and if you will be pleaſed to make uſe of my ſhort perſpective, it will ſhew you as plainy the ſpots in this Man, as ever <hi>Galilejes</hi> did in the Moon.</p>
            <p>And to ſave your time and money, I ſhall briefly ſhew you his open falſhoods, his cloſer couched tales, with his contradictions, juglings, railings, blaſphemy and impiety, and then ſhall come and take off what he would by theſe caſt upon the Parliament cauſe, eſpecially in relation to their late proceedings.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He who hath been pleaſed to affirm, <hi>That the Knaves</hi> (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſome eminent honeſt Men) <hi>lyed like Saints,</hi> will neither ſpeake truth as becomes a Saint, or lye, we wil uſe his own broad phraſe, for it's probable he underſtands his own Language beſt, like a Knave; for he tels ſuch palpable ones, that almoſt every one can contradict. I know not what deſign this Lord of the Manor of Barley Broath could have in thus doing, unleſſe he intended to purchaſe another Hel; but let him take heed the pottage there be not too hot.</p>
            <p>Or goes by that rule <hi>calumniare fortiter aliquid harebit,</hi> throw dirt by ſhovels full on thy Adverſary, and ſome will ſtick. It is I confeſſe, and hath been the practice of all the Malignant Scriblers ſo to do, and yet we may thank God that we have been little loſers by it: for they have engaged againſt Heaven by it, as well as againſt us, and have made God their enemy.</p>
            <p>Firſt in his Epiſtle he avers, That there were men on purpoſe mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among the <hi>Surry</hi> Petitioners to raife a whoop, and diſorder them, that they might be taken in a toyl, and fallen upon with Horſe and Foot; and that Gentlemen of as good quality as the Generall had their Pockets, Cloakes, Hats, Swords, Horſes, and Doublets plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
            <p>Had he named one either in quality a Lord, or Lord Generall, it had not been Gentlemen, and ſo had been falſe, yet he can never do
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153720:8"/>that; but this is the truth of the buſineſſe, The Surrey men by the opportunity of ſo many Taverns, Alehouſes, and boon Companions, being gotten drunk, violently ruſhed into the Hall, Lobby, &amp;c. where they both abuſed the Members, affronted the Guard, whooped and roar'd (being ecchoed by the Crue without, made up of all the ſcum of that end the Town) in ſo hideous a manner, as if they deſired ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to deafen the Houſe, than to have been heard by them; a great number of them being gotten into the Court of Requeſt, danced croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and thwacking their cudgles, the moſt perfect whoop <hi>Barnaby,</hi> the moſt abſolute drunken Moriſco, that you ever ſaw, reeling a kind of Hay to the harſh muſick of their throats, and ratling noiſe of their hob-nail'd ſhooes, as if the <hi>Bacchanals</hi> came to celebrate the <hi>Dyoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian Orgies,</hi> or took the High Court for a May-Pole, and ſo came to play their old May-games about it: but as if it were not enough to have given them this alarm, they boaſted to beat up the Houſes quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſwearing, they would have their Petition granted, or they would pluck the Members out by the eares, and thus Pot-valiant began to throng to the dore. The Guard being unwilling to be pinion'd in that drunken Crowd, where if need were, they ſhould not be able to uſe their armes, charged them to ſtand off, upon this they crowded higher, and were anſwered by the Dunghils without, and preſuming on their numbers violently ruſhed on the Guard; but ſome Horſe and Foot being in a readineſſe, as having had good warning by their bragging,<note place="margin">In vino veritas.</note> and ſuppoſing that being in drink, they meant as they ſaid, came in the nick, reſcued the Guard, and totally routed them who were more than enough diſordered before.</p>
            <p>This was done, and who can deny but fit to be done; and for what they loſt they may thank themſelves for beginning a tumult, and their ſuburb Companions, who were excellently dexterous to help unbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then them of Cloaks, Hats, &amp;c. I am confident that when they were ſober, had they but known their own incivility in affronting the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and their Guard, they would have thanked God, and thoſe they abuſed, that they ſped ſo wel. Had this vindicative old <hi>Bedlam</hi> bin Captain of the Guard, I might have related more than all he hath done, and that truly too, but God be thanked the curſt Cow hath but ſhort Horns, Lying and Rayling are his Bounds, thither he can goe, and no further.</p>
            <p>He affirmes,<note place="margin">Part 1. p. 86.87.</note> 
               <hi>That when the Boyes made the Tumult,</hi> April, 8 <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153720:8"/>1648. <hi>the Lord Generall</hi> Cromwel <hi>followed the Souldiers in the Reare, animating them to ſhoot, and ſpit them, and to ſpare neither Man, Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man nor Child, and crying out to them to fire the City: That the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers cut and wounded all they met.</hi> How falſe this is will appeare by the ſmall number of hurt or killed, and thoſe that were hurt, being but a little ſlightly ſlaſh'd to terrifie and warn others, rather than out of any deſire to miſchiefe them; beſides I appeal to thoſe thouſands who ſtood at their dores, windowes, and in the ſtreet, and ſaw the buſines, yet were never ſpoken to by the Souldiers, unleſſe when they ſuppoſed there might be danger, and then too, onely to take heed to themſelvs, whether they did not ſee the Souldiers ſhoot high on purpoſe, and where they ſtruck once with the edge ſtrike twenty times with the flat of their Swords: but had the Souldiers been Cabs, and <hi>Rupert, Goring,</hi> or the Great Chiefe at <hi>Leiceſter</hi> Himſelf in the Rear, then I doubt not but <hi>Clem</hi> might have been in the Right. Alas poor <hi>Clem</hi> what il luck thou hadſt, that they were not the men.</p>
            <p>He averres,<note place="margin">Part 1. p. 97.</note> 
               <hi>That the Lord Gen. Cromwell ſold his Welch Priſoners for</hi> 12d. <hi>a head to be ſent into barbarous Plantation.</hi> Had they not bin Cavaleers he would have put in Hornes and all I warrant you: but here he ſhews a little more wit in his anger, he layes the ſcene a little farther off; yet though all <hi>London</hi> cannot give him the Lye, all <hi>Wales</hi> can, which knowes the Common Souldiers were ſent to their owne homes, and the Officers were to quit <hi>England</hi> for a time, three or four only excepted, of which only <hi>Poyer</hi> ſuffered; it may be ſome poore Scoundrels, who either had no homes, or durſt not go to a home if they had one, were willing to go to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantations, <hi>Virginia,</hi> the <hi>Barbadoes &amp;c.</hi> barbarous and <hi>Barbado</hi> begins indeed ſomething a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, yet dare I affirm, that all theſe Plantations he tearms barbarous, cannot ſhew ſo uncivil, ſo barbarous, ſo impious a wretch as the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>London</hi> can.</p>
            <p>He ſaith Mr. Gurdon <hi>made a motion to have the Ladies Norwich, Capell, and her Children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Part 1 p 101.</note> 
               <hi>ſent to the Generall to be ſet in the Front of the Army in ſtorming Colcheſter, and that he was ſeconded by many more.</hi> Had he had ſo little honeſty as to tel tales out of the Houſe, yet he might have had ſo much modeſty as not to tel them ſo, that the whole Houſe muſt contradict him; but ſuppoſe it were true, and that Maſter <hi>Gourdon,</hi> and other Gentlemen did motion that thoſe might be ſent to be ſet in the Front of our Army, when <hi>Norwich, Capell, Lucas,</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153720:9"/>thoſe ſhould ſalley out with the Committee ſet in their Front, what great buſineſs had this been to deterre a barbarous Enemy from cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thoſe Gentlemen to be murder'd, whom they had carried away contrary to all Articles of War, being men in their own Country and not in Arms, and kept too by denying to exchange them? But then He ſaith <hi>That they never intended to uſe the Committee ſo,</hi> then Mr. <hi>Gour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> never deſired to have them uſed ſo, and to prove this, he ſaith, <hi>Ruſhworth</hi> reported <hi>they were well uſed,</hi> thank the General, who ſent them in their dyet, and their ſcarcity within, who would never have granted that, but to ſave their own proviſions; alſo they were not ſet in the Front, good reaſon, becauſe the Common ſoldiers in <hi>Colcheſter</hi> mutined, and would not ſally out, which if they would have done, their great Commanders had determined to doe it, and had ſet the time too, and this hath been affirmed by the Committee themſelves in my hearing, who were certainly informed of it by the Cabs themſelvs, which was to have been on the Thurſday before the Town was yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; but the Souldiers being aſcertained that their Officers intended to ſalley out, and if they could by their help break through, to run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way being well horſt, and leave them to the fury of our Soldier, whom they knew would be much enraged to have been made inſtrùmentall in the deaths of the Committee ſo baſely murthered by their Officers, and themſelvs too, who permitted it, mutined, and that ſo highly and unanimouſly, that their Officers had much adoe to pacifie them; and thus you may ſee the verity and ingenuity of old <hi>Clem,</hi> who knew all this as wel as I, in telling the ſtory.</p>
            <p>He affirms,<note place="margin">Part 1: p. 102.</note> 
               <hi>That the Lord Generall</hi> Fairfax <hi>having gotten together the Trained Men of</hi> Suffolk <hi>and</hi> Eſſex <hi>to aſſiſt him, put them in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorn hope in all his ſtormings of Colcheſter, and drove them on with his Horſe, uſing them as the</hi> Turk <hi>doth his</hi> Aſaphi <hi>to dead the firſt fury and edge of the Enemy, that his</hi> Ianiſaries <hi>at the laſt may come on with the more ſafety, and carry the buſineſſe.</hi> A Barbarous falſehood, as the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia of two Counties, and an Army can witneſſe; ſpeak out you inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Gentlemen in both Counties, whom he hath made ſuch tame Slaves and Cowards: but the gallant demeanour of the Lord Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and Army is ſo deeply rooted in the memories of thoſe <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke</hi> and <hi>Eſſex</hi> Troopes and Companies, that ſuch a calumnie as this can never pluck it up; it is needleſſe to ſay more therefore to this.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:153720:9"/>
            <p>He ſaith, <hi>That M: Gen.</hi> Skippon <hi>hath ſecured his perſonall Eſtate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 1. p. 120.</note> 
               <hi>his Wife and Children beyond Sea, and thereby hath withdrawn all pledges of his fidelity, and is here but in the nature of a Souldier of Fortune.</hi> This is a lye as viſible as the Major Gen: Wife and Children are every day; but the Major Gen: hath ſpent as much blound in defence of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as this wretch hath waſted Ink to deſtroy it.</p>
            <p>He averrs, <hi>That there is not one Aſſembly-man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 1. p. 174.</note> 
               <hi>but is illegally thruſt into another mans benefice.</hi> We need not go farre to diſprove this; ſpeak thou O <hi>London</hi> for the reſt, which haſt four Aſſembly men who never had any ſequeſtred Benefice, to wit, Doctor <hi>Gouge,</hi> Mr. <hi>Caryll,</hi> Mr. <hi>Walker,</hi> Mr. <hi>Calamie,</hi> and contradict him.</p>
            <p>He affirmeth, <hi>That the fight againſt the</hi> Scots, <hi>was little better than a beating up of quarters for</hi> 20 <hi>miles together, for ſo far the</hi> Scotch <hi>Army lay ſcattered in their Quarters, their Horſe ſo farre diſtant from their Foot they could bring them no ſeaſonable relief.</hi> A very broad Lye; for the very firſt day they were drawn up into ſo large a body that 2. Regiments were left to hinder their overwinging, and ſo incloſing our Army at ſuch diſtance, that they had little or no employment the firſt fight; <hi>Hamilton</hi> ſtill ſhogging down with Reſerves, and bringing freſh hands to maintain the advantages of the Lanes and paſſe he had againſt ours, and ſo not advancing in bredth, as it was ſuppoſed he would.</p>
            <p>But, ſuppoſe it had been ſo the firſt day; this was nothing to the ſecond, or third day, on which he confeſſes the fight continued, nay and rails at Lieut Gen: <hi>Baylie,</hi> for delivering up the arms of the foot after at the paſſe at <hi>Warrington,</hi> by which it appeares he thought the firſt, ſecond, and third dayes loſſe, not ſo conſiderable, but that <hi>Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> might have maintained that paſſe, had he not been a Traytor; but this is all any man ſhall get by engaging for the Cavaliers; with old <hi>Clems</hi> favour we may well return the <hi>Turke</hi> (he beſtowed before on the L. Gen:) to him and his gang, whoſe <hi>Baſhaw's</hi> head muſt go for their ill Fortune. You ſhall never hear an <hi>Aulicus, Pragma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus, Clem,</hi> or any inferiour ſucking Cab confeſſe their ſide was bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, but they lay it on the treachery of one or other of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders in chief; thus <hi>Rupert's</hi> health muſt not be drunk, for his tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery in delivering up <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> Col. <hi>Fielding</hi> muſt be condemned for yielding <hi>Reading,</hi> and <hi>Windebank</hi> ſhot for loſing a paltry little Houſe; and thus are the <hi>Scots</hi> rewarded with the names of Traitors, and Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153720:10"/>for their good will to the Cabs, and making ſuch a coſtly journey to help them: one would think that if they had either ſenſe or reaſon, they might long ere this have been convinced, that it is no impoſſible thing for the Cabs to be beaten, as at <hi>Marſton Moor,</hi> the Battle of <hi>Namptwich,</hi> the fight neer <hi>Cheſter,</hi> where <hi>Poyntz</hi> commanded in chief, and neer <hi>Stow</hi> of the old, where old <hi>Aſhly</hi> was taken with innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble other places, where the moſt obſtinate Cabs commanded. But you may ſee what metal old <hi>Clem</hi> is made of, he is no Cavalier, not he alas! he abhors them, lyes and ſlanders, as the Devill doth Holie-water.</p>
            <p>Theſe out of many hundreds I have ſet down to convince you, what a due reſpect you ought to have to theſe following ſtories; for which he can ſhew neither ſenſe or reaſon, and which are only mounted on the baſis of <hi>Clems</hi> bare word.</p>
            <p>He affirmeth,<note place="margin">P. 2. p. 195.</note> 
               <hi>That Col.</hi> Popham, <hi>when he had loſt moſt of his Men at</hi> Kingſale, <hi>beſides divers Ships, was commanded to conceal the evill newes, and to tell the Houſe, that he had left</hi> Kingſale <hi>blocked up with ten ſhips, and the Seas ſecured.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Speaker bled in private</hi> (how came <hi>Clem</hi> to know it then?<note place="margin">P. 2. p. 212</note>) 15000 l. <hi>towards the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Expedition, to have the Charge taken off a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</hi> I cannot think <hi>Clem</hi> was the Surgeon, yet it may be <hi>Clem</hi> going to bed in a covetous humour, might dreame he held the Baſon he bled into.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Lord Generall</hi> Cromwell <hi>writ Letters to Col.</hi> Iones, <hi>how heartleſſe his Souldiers were,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 2. p. 229</note> 
               <hi>and that unleſſe he did by ſome ſucceſſefull ſallie leſſen their terror, he ſhould not be able to get them on ſhipboard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Letter was intercepted by the Major that brought news that <hi>Dublin</hi> was taken, in one of the Egg-ſhels which the great <hi>Mogul</hi> ſent to tranſport the 3000 <hi>Lorrain</hi> Horſe into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſo <hi>Clem</hi> ſaw it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Lord Gen.</hi> Cromwell <hi>writ Letters to ſome of the Councel of State by Col.</hi> Monk <hi>himſelf,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 2. p. 230</note> 
               <hi>deſiring them for ſatisfaction of the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and People, to treat with Col.</hi> Monk <hi>to take the whole buſineſs upon himſelf, of his Treatie with</hi> Owen Roe Oneale, and to juſtifie this, he tels you, <hi>the L. Preſident</hi> Bradſhaw <hi>laugh'd when he reproved Col.</hi> Monk <hi>for it.</hi> You ſee he was by, and ſaw all, will you not believe this too?</p>
            <p>He doth not tel us where he heard the comand given to Col. <hi>Popham,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:153720:10"/>nor how or where he ſaw theſe Letters; and it was well he did not, for it would but have made a more circumſtantiall tale, and have hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped up the meaſure of his lies the more, and yet never a whit have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantaged him: For how can any think it poſſible he could have heard or ſeen them, when all theſe men knew him too well to truſt him with ſuch ſecreſie, and he himſelf tels us boaſtingly, that he was alwayes oppoſite to both Presbyterians and Independents, and could never be drawn to any of their ſecret meetings, whilſt he was in the Houſe? and yet now he can tel things which he himſelf relates to be carried with the greateſt ſecreſie; if we could but find the hearts to believe him we need never wonder that he refuſed to go to their ſecret meetings; for what need he do that, who we ſee can tell the moſt clandeſtine tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaction without a being at it? but formal Lyes, and formall Prayers, are no wonders in an old Epiſcopall Malignant; ſuch an one is ſo for ſet forms, that he cannot ſerve the Devil out of one, or bring out a lie or ſlander, but it muſt be in Pontificalibus.</p>
            <p>And now you may judge, whether <hi>Theodorus Verax,</hi> or <hi>Clemens tam ficti, pravi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tenax,</hi> be the trueſt Latine, for the Author of this Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of Independency. For my part, I have thought that man conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of an ill Title, who will be the judge in his own cauſe, nay aſſured that any juſt and underſtanding Iudge will give ſentence againſt him; and pray what think you off this here, can you ſuppoſe that ever he had had the Title of <hi>Theodorus Verax,</hi> unleſſe he had beſtowed it on himſelf; <hi>Honor eſt externum ſignum</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arist.</hi> l. 1. Rhet. c. 5. &amp; l 4. Eth. c. 3. &amp; l. 1. Eth: c. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Et eſt in Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante potius quam Honorato,</hi> but why ſhould we talk of morall Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie to him? And if he had deſired the Honour to wear Truths li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, he had better have writ himſelf <hi>Verax</hi> in his Book, than on the Title page, but I ſuppoſe he did it to make the Title Page bear it's part, and that it might be ſuitable to the reſt of the Book for falſhood.</p>
            <p>And now I come to his contradictions, and ſhall make his Book confute it ſelf, as I have made it confute his Title, and among many take theſe.</p>
            <p>This Fellow who was choſen into the Houſe, ſate there, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth to have been on the Parliaments part, who cryes out,<note place="margin">Part 1 p 15</note> 
               <hi>they have changed their Principles,</hi> and affirmes, <hi>that he had ſerved the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment faithfully from the beginning; had taken as much pains, and runne as many hazards, as moſt men in their ſervice, wherein he had loſt his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153720:11"/>health and above</hi> 7000 <hi>l. of his Eſtate, that he contented himſelf to ſerve his Country gratis.</hi> Note here that he accounts the Parliament cauſe, the Cauſe of his Countrey, and yet is he not aſhamed to maintain, That the King neither ought nor could part with his Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Voice, and Militia.</p>
            <p>And can any man hold this who hath ſerved the Parliament from the beginning, &amp; affirm he ſtands to his firſt Principles, when the Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia and Negative Voice were the only two points in open Conteſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King and Parliament, upon which the War was grounded? for the King, whatever he meant, yet promiſed fair about Religion, and redreſs of grievances.</p>
            <p>Or can <hi>Clem</hi> ſhake hands with <hi>Pryn,</hi> unleſſe as <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> once before did to Crucifie Chriſt again in his Members?</p>
            <p>Thus he ſaith a Phoenix aroſe out of his Majeſties Aſhes, that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent iſſue of his Brain,<note place="margin">P. 2. p. 138</note> intituled, <hi>The Portraicture of his Sacred Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, &amp;c.</hi> a Book full fraught with Wiſdom Divine and Humane, yet the very firſt Page of that Book, and the firſt Page of his ſo interfere that one gives the other the Lye. For his affirms, that at laſt by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, his Majeſty was neceſſitated to call a Parliament; That avers that he called it of his own choice and inclination, as thinking the right way of Parliaments moſt ſafe for his Crown, and beſt pleaſing to his People. And for my part, had old <hi>Clem</hi> gon on as he here begun, I would never have taxed him for falſhood.</p>
            <p>Behold then, that unleſſe lying be a piece of Wiſdom Divine and Humane (which yet by his practice one would be eaſily perſwaded to believe <hi>Clem</hi> thinks) he hath not only contradicted himſelf, poor Knave, but his Great Maſters young Phoenix forſooth, unmanner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſlave.</p>
            <p>But if it be ſuch a Phoenix, it aroſe out of ſome others aſhes, for the King was not burnt, neither as yet is crumbled to duſt: and if it be ſuch a <hi>Pallas,</hi> yet it looks as more likely to have iſſued from the brain of a <hi>Mercury</hi> than a <hi>love.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Palladis Aves, <hi>birds dedicated to</hi> Pallas.</note> For my part if I ſhould paſſe my judgment I muſt give for the latter, as the more proper compariſon, becauſe the Idol's triumphant Chariot is drawn by Owles.</p>
            <p>And now you may ſee <hi>Clems</hi> Logick is as bad as his Ethicks, and that there is no more truth than manners in his Propoſitions. For un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe contradictories can at once be both truth, <hi>Clem</hi> writes miſerably falſe; but more of this will appear in his ſubſequent jugling, which is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153720:11"/>notorious in the very firſt part of his Hiſiory, which he ſtiles a <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the two Iuntoe's</hi> Presbyterian <hi>and</hi> Independent.</p>
            <p>Here by the way, I would fain know which was the Parliament <hi>Clem</hi> ſerved, ſith the Presbyterians and Independents were two Iunto's? Prelatical fellowes there could not be then, unleſſe perjured; for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Member had taken the Covenant. If then the Presbyterians and Independents were two Iunto's, and there was a Parliament, it muſt conſiſt of Prelaticall perjur'd perſons, or of ſuch as <hi>Clem,</hi> who were neither for any Religion, any Doctrine, or any diſcipline, and ſo forſworn, yea Atheiſts to boot; and were there enough ſuch in the Houſe to conſtitute a Parliament, indeed we may all rejoyce that the Army ſecluded them, and need never wonder at the tricks they play'd there; but we ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak more of this hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Again, Behold how <hi>Clem,</hi> who would be thought a great aſſertor of Parliamentary Privilege, and rayles at the Army for ſecluding the Members, here hath outed the major part, if not all the Parliament, and junto'd them: for I am certain there was not one then in the Houſe, but profeſſed himſelf either a Presbyterian, or Independent; though ſome in a more rigid, others in a more moderate way.</p>
            <p>In this Myſtery he reckons up what he and his fellow Members did while in the Houſe together, with their good Lordſhips, Committees, Sequeſtrators, Treaſurers, and whole rabble of Receivers, Deceivers, &amp;c. and all to bring an <hi>odium</hi> upon the Parliament (for this part was written while <hi>Clem</hi> was in the Houſe) yea upon his ful and free Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as he is afterwards many times pleaſed to call it, when it may ſerve his turn.</p>
            <p>But the Myſtery of this was to give the alarum to the ſecond War, and exaſperate the people to joyn with the Cabs to deſtroy the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and re-inthrone his great Maſter, which was the only buſineſſe <hi>Clem</hi> got into the Houſe for; yet read what he ſaith of them, and though you cannot believe all, yet you may finde ſomething true, and then tell me whether they deſerved not to be plucked out, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they had not in the higheſt manner forfeited their truſt, and whether they were not as great Tyrants, as Him they had outed?</p>
            <p>They ſate taxing and polling, yet paid not their Forces; they ſate Voting one another money, yet paid neither the publicke, nor their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153720:12"/>own private debts, but under the Privilege of Peers, and Parliament men protected themſelves, and whom they lifted from all due proceſſe of Law, and that they might be ſure to ſit long enough, they neither went about to reſtore the old, or erect a new way of Government; <hi>ſed tempora mutantur, Clem,</hi> and his gang are unrooſted, the Army is conſtantly paid, Free-quarter taken off, the Navy trebled, and well paid too, many publique debts ſatisfied, a Lord, or a Parliament man muſt pay his too, or may be ſued and made to do it, the Rebels cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to a ſtrict account in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Parliament cauſe vindicated in <hi>England,</hi> Iuſtice executed on the Grand Delinquents in both, a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth eſtabliſhed, and all honeſt true-hearted Engliſh-men, if they will be ſecured from comming under the power of an enraged Tyrant.</p>
            <p>For that which he objects, <hi>That when ihe Parliament had</hi> 4 <hi>or</hi> 5. <hi>ſeverall Armies, the Tax was but</hi> 52000 <hi>l. that now it is</hi> 90000 <hi>l.</hi> per menſem, Be pleaſed to conſider theſe things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That <hi>London,</hi> and the beſt affected Counties paid as much then or more, becauſe divers were under contribution to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</item>
               <item>2. That admit all were reduced, yet Freequarter was ſtil continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and many other aſſeſſments.</item>
               <item>3. We may affirm, and that truly, That the Parliament hath as many Souldiers now in pay in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> as they had then, though not under ſo many ſeveral Commanders, and thrice as many Sea Forces.</item>
               <item>4. That the greateſt part of the Delinquents fines which amounted to a very conſiderable ſum came into their Coffers then.</item>
               <item>5. That the forces are now paid conſtantly, and Free-quarter taken off, and the Tax now leſſened to 60000 <hi>l. per menſem.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>As for the Exciſe, Biſhops, Deans and Chapters Lands, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining Fines of Delinquents, they are hardly ſufficient to pay off debts charged in courſe, and the Intereſt money the other had runne into; as for the Cuſtoms, they are not by farre ſufficient to defray the charge of the ſhipping: and thus you may ſee the validity of this cavil, which may ſuffice to unfold one Myſtery of this Hocus Pocus, this <hi>Clem</hi> of no ſide, for he would puzzle a man that eyes him not well to finde out what he is.</p>
            <p>He rayles againſt the Independent party and the Army, becauſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153720:12"/>they oppoſed the disbanding the Army, ſaying <hi>their continuing in arms was a manifeſt act of Treaſon and Rebellion; that a Schiſmaticall Faction in the two Honſes complyed with them, betraying and proſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the very being, honour, and all the fundamentall rights and privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of this, and future Parliaments, to an Army of Rebells, who refuſe to obey their Maſters and diſband.</hi> Note here the Independent Members and the Army are to be rendred odious.</p>
            <p>And yet he tels us, <hi>That beſide the City to aw the adjacent South and eaſt Countries, to ſuppreſs the remoter, the Presbyterians kept up ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land Garriſons, had the</hi> Scots, <hi>and</hi> Pointz <hi>ſupernumerary Forces for the, North, and in the Weſt</hi> (<hi>under colour of ſending men for</hi> Ireland) <hi>they kept upon Free quarter, and pay of the Countrey many ſupernumerary Rogiments and Troops, moſt Cavaliers, at leaſt five times as many as they really intended to tranſport, theſe were allwayes going, but never gone, ſomething is and ever ſhall he wanting, untill</hi> Sir Thomas Fairfaix <hi>his Army be disbanded, and then it is thought the diſguiſe will fall off, and theſe ſupernumeraries appear a new Model'd Army, theſe lewd ſupernu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meraries, moſt of which ſwear they will not go for</hi> Ireland, <hi>vowing they will cut the throats of the Roundheads, the Country that is amazed fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring they are kept on Free-quarter by a Cavalieriſh party, for ſome Cavalieriſh deſigne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Note here the Presbyterians are to be rayl'd at, and thoſe that p. 33. are the Houſes, who for the eaſe of the people, Voted a disban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Army, are here a Presbyterian Iunto, who would disband this Army to modell a new one, whoſe Conſciences ſhall not befoole their wits where matter of gain appears, but be more pliable to their deſires, and be one of the Cords wherewith the Presbyterian <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thous</hi> will drive their triumphant Chariot.</p>
            <p>Note alſo the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> his Army, which even now were Rebels and Traytors, who abominated nothing more than to return to their old trades againe, is here an Army excellently diſciplined, having the viſible mark of Gods favour upon their actions, and that the Houſes are queſtioned, nay termed a Iunto for endeavouring to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band them.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Note how old <hi>Clem</hi> would ſeem a great Enemy to Cavaliers, and very fearfull of a Cavalieriſh deſigne, only to ingratiate with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men; when there is not a more deſperate Malignant ſlave in all <hi>Europe,</hi> as his own Tenets do evidence? as for example.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:153720:13"/>
            <p>In his Exhortatory concluſion to the Engliſh Nation, he avers, <hi>That it is evident King</hi> Charls <hi>from the beginning took up deſerſive arms to maintain Religion, Laws, Libertyes, and the ancient fundamentall being of Parliaments;</hi> could a <hi>Digby</hi> or a <hi>Nicholas</hi> have ſaid more? could an <hi>Aulicus</hi> or a <hi>Prag.</hi> have railed at, and belyed the Parliament and Army more, or have writ more falſe ſtories than this fellow hath done? and yet, O hee is affraid of the Cavaliers; but this will appeare more plainly in our ſubſequent diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>But I wil firſt give you an Hiſtory, that you may more eaſily diſcern the myſtery of this fellow.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Clem,</hi> when <hi>Briſtol</hi> was delivered up to <hi>Rupert</hi> by Col. <hi>Fienns</hi> upon honourable terms (had they been kept by that perfidious plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer) who ſo zelous, who ſo active, at leſt in ſhew for the Parliament, cauſe, as this old <hi>Clem,</hi> who accuſed the Governour of Cowardiſe and treachery, for not defending that City to the uttermoſt extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? then forſooth the King, who now hath the juſt cauſe from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, was an Enemy to be fought againſt to the laſt man, and what was the myſtery of this but to ſet our party together by the ears? He knew Colonell <hi>Fiennes</hi> had many great and noble friends, who had a mighty influence on the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> his Army; He knew that Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> and Sir <hi>Arthur Haflerigge</hi> were ſtrongly fortified in the good opinion of the multitude, and ſo hoped there would be ſome tugging.</p>
            <p>But that Noble Gentleman Col. <hi>Fiennes,</hi> whoſe innocency the Parliament hath ſince vindicated, being contented to ſubmit to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, as chuſing rather to fall alone, than indanger his Country, though in that act ſhe might ſeem a ſtepmother, fruſtrated the deſign in part, though the animoſities then created in the parties cauſed ſome fatall conſequences, as the loſſe in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> the exaſperated Souldiery being contented to behold their Rivals cudgell'd by the Common enemy.</p>
            <p>Behold therefore who were the Incendiaries, and what was the cauſe that enforced the Parliament to new model their Army, it was <hi>Clem</hi> and ſuch Blades, though he would lay it on others.</p>
            <p>You may ſee alſo the Myſtery of <hi>Clems</hi> appearing for the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and what his aim was in getting into the Houſe: He did firſt appear an eager oppoſit to the Cavaliers to get in among them, where he might ſit and give aim, by diſcovering their Counſels to his great
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153720:13"/>Maſter. This <hi>Clem</hi> was one of the Setters, who; beſides all other miſchiefs, were to betray thoſe who faithfully and freely diſcharged their Truſts to their Country, that when opportunity did ſerve, CHARLES might call them to account, as he uſually did at the end of Parliaments, as the commitment of Members evidently ſhewes, which was ſo inſeparable an attendant on Parliaments, that a man may conceive CHARLES ſummoned Parliaments only to find out thoſe who were not willing to be ſlaves, that he might either cajole them, or if Court-proof ruine them.</p>
            <p>Thus were <hi>Savill, Wentworth, Culpepper,</hi> and <hi>Digby,</hi> whoſe publike Spirits ſeem'd Hobgoblings to tyrannicall intereſt, conjured down by an <hi>Ave Marie,</hi> and a little Court-holy-water; and thus were <hi>Elliot, Valentine, Pym,</hi> and <hi>Strode,</hi> written in black Characters in CHARLS his Dooms-day Book, and either to be deſtroyed in Priſon or perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually immur'd, iron fetters being the Chains wherewith the Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for thy freedom were rewarded O <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Clem</hi> being fruſtrated in this deſign, He hath now publiſhed their Speeches to the Son, adding and forging what he liſts, to render them obvious to the rage of an Enemy nurſed up in ſlaughter, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers tyrannicall Principles, and no doubt Mothers Religion.</p>
            <p>Thus hath this fellow dared to violate that ſecreſie which ſhould be ſacred among Members of the Houſe, and to accuſe Members for what they did in the Houſe, though he bawl againſt the Army for impeaching the 11. Members upon actions in the Houſe, and decryes it as the greateſt breach of privilege, and violation of the Covenant, and yet he averrs, <hi>He hath adventured to vindicate our Religion, Laws, and Liberties with his pen, in purſuance of the Covenant;</hi> as if it were law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for him to ſay, and do any thing; it is a breach of Covenant in the Army, it is a purſuance of it in him.</p>
            <p>Bluſh ye Heavens and tremble O Earth, at the diſmall impudence of this Wretch, who dares thus openly take that Covenant in his mouth, and profeſſe to have taken it, which he ſo horribly hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as may thus appear.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>He every where cries up the moſt desperate Anti-covenanters, as</hi> Montroſſe, <hi>one whom the whole State and Kick of</hi> Scotland <hi>have ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced, as the moſt bloody Excommunicate Traytor and Rebell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>He admires, and praiſes</hi> Hamilton, <hi>who by a Malignant Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and force overſwayed the Parliament of</hi> Scotland, <hi>exerciſing the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153720:14"/>higheſt tyrauny and oppreſſion over thoſe Covenanters, who would not joyn with him in that horrid violation of the Covenant, the Invaſion of</hi> England, <hi>and conjunction with</hi> Langdale, <hi>and his deſperate crue of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-covenanters, yea and juſtifies that action.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>He averres it was a vain thing to deſire the late King to take the Covenant, who could not take it but he ſhould prophane Gods name, and ferſwear himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>He profeſſes himſelf oppoſite both to the Presbyterians and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents, as the common diſturbers of the Church; railes againſt the Presbyterian Miniſters and the Aſſembly, calling them wicked</hi> Simons, <hi>that ſlander the godly</hi> Onias, <hi>to out him of his Prieſts place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>He jeeres them and their Government; ſaying, The popiſh Clergy draw all civill affairs, publike and private, under their juriſdistion and cognizance,</hi> quatenus <hi>there is</hi> peccatum <hi>in all humane actions, the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> quatenus <hi>there is</hi> ſcandalum, <hi>what oddes?</hi> peccatum <hi>is the Mother,</hi> ſcandalum <hi>is the Daughter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus he is not aſhamed to abuſe the moſt ſacred tie a Solemn oath; what regard then is to be given to his counterfeit pretence of making a conſcience of Oaths? all thoſe poſitive and abſolute articles which contein the main end of the Covenant, are nothing with him, but that clauſe for preſervation of the Kings Perſon, though limited with a ſubordination to Religion and Liberty, is ſo ſacred, becauſe for his turne, that it muſt be kept, though contrary to the words as well as meaning, even in deſtruction of Religion and Liberty.</p>
            <p>Thus having mocked God, he deſcends to abuſe men, and thoſe not of the ordinary ſort, but Members of Parliament, the High and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Court; as in his Century, which he ſtiles <hi>A Liſt of the names of the Members of the Houſe, obſerving which are Officers of the Army contrary to the ſelf-denying Ordinance, together with ſuch ſummes of money, Offices, and Lands, as they have given to themſelves for ſervice done and to be done againſt the King and Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a rare fellow to profeſſe <hi>he hath ſerved the Parliament faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and that he hath not changed his Principles:</hi> but ſhould we admit it to be as he ſaith, may not the houſe diſpenſe with one of their own Ordinances? but behold the jugler.</p>
            <p>For firſt there was not one Member continued in command but the now L. Gen: <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and that upon the entreaty of the Army, yet he writes, as if they had their commands ſtill: The Ordinance
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153720:14"/>did not ſay every one that had a Command ſhould leave the Houſe, but that every one of the Houſe ſhould leave their Commands, and ſo they did. Here is one juggle.</p>
            <p>Then he muſters a great many, who have been choſen into the Houſe ſince the Ordinance, and end of the firſt Warre, and had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands in their ſeverall Counties, whoſe commands ceaſed of courſe, and where are theſe touched in the Ordinance?</p>
            <p>Others there are who being Officers of the Army, were admitted into the Houſe upon the late elections, and never queſtioned for their commands: but this peremptory wrech who would ſeem to underſtand the Ordinance better than the whole Houſe that made it, yet knows wel enough the reaſon of that Ordinance, as having had a great hand in working the miſchief, which that was made to prevent.</p>
            <p>The emulations of our ſeverall Commanders had nigh ruin'd all; there was no way better to remove the difference, and quench the flame, than by calling home all from command; thus none could plead an injury, his Rivall being in the ſame capacity with himſelf: this was done, and it proved excellent phyſick, but the cure being done, what need of the medicine? Sure this Fellow himſelf would think that man mad, that ſhould rail to ſee another that is recovered leave his phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick potions, eſpecially with his Doctors Licence; and yet this this Bedlam doth.</p>
            <p>For the Offices they were void, ſome by death, others by Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency; and is it not more juſt, more beneficiall for the publike, yea, more like a Parliament to beſtow, than ſell places: but the wretch bought his in the Exchequer, and envies therefore at the good of his Neighbours who did not ſo.</p>
            <p>And if it be fitter to beſtow than ſell publike Offices, to whom could they better give ſuch, than to honeſt men; and whom could the Parliament be more confident of, than ſuch whoſe integrity and love to their Country was ſeen by them every day, both in their Speeches within dores, and actions without? and truly I am induced to thinke the better of their choice, becauſe I finde not <hi>Clem</hi> in the Lift: For if we cannot ſay that no Knaves get Offices, yet we may affirme that all Knaves did not; as for Example, old <hi>Clem's</hi> mouth is not ſtopt.</p>
            <p>For money and Lands, was it not the higheſt juſtice to reward thoſe Gentlemen who had ſuffered, out of the Eſtates of ſuch upon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153720:15"/>whom his great Maſter had beſtowed theirs? beſides what thing ſo barbarous, ſo greedy, ſo envious, ſo like old little tutchy <hi>Clem,</hi> would accuſe a Parliament for rewarding their Members for their valor and fidelity in defending their Conntryes liberty.</p>
            <p>His great Maſter could make <hi>Rupert</hi> Duke of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> for murdering and plundering in <hi>England, Montroſſe</hi> a Marqueſſe, for killing and and robbing in <hi>Scotland;</hi> and <hi>Antrim</hi> a Marqueſſe for joyning with the Rebels in <hi>Ireland;</hi> beſides this beggarly fellow a Lord, that a Baronet, another a Knight, and beſtow honeſt Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens eſtates on them, yet we hear nothing of this, <hi>Clem</hi> makes no Centuries of them.</p>
            <p>Alas! <hi>Digby</hi> deſerved to be Secretary for penning ſo many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, wherein God and man were mocked in Print, as much as in <hi>Clems</hi> book, and <hi>Nichols</hi> merited as much for lying as faſt as <hi>Clem</hi> for his great Maſter.</p>
            <p>But the Parliament cannot beſtow a reward on thoſe, who have ventured their lives and fortunes in their Countryes defence, who have thought nothing too dear to part with for Religion and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who with the hazard of their private, have ſav'd the publike, but they muſt be branded by him with the Mark of waſters and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Publique Treaſure; it is reward enough he thinks, for any who have ſerved the Parliament, if they proſper and overcome, to obtein the Title of <hi>Stubbornly ſtout,</hi> as he rewards the Lord General <hi>Eſſex,</hi> or of <hi>Brutiſh valour,</hi> as the Lord Generall <hi>Fairfox.</hi> If they are overpowred, and will be ſo prudent as to make a vertue of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, and do what they may, if they cannot do what they would, with the Title of Coward and Traytor, as he did Col. <hi>Fines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See the irrationall barbarity of this fellow, who when he pleaſeth will have every thing Cowardice and treachery under the degree of Deſperateneſſe;<note place="margin">As in Col. <hi>Nathaniell Fiennes</hi> Caſe.</note> and when he liſts again, call the moſt ſober valour Brutiſh and Stubborn ſtoutnes, but one would think, one ſo implaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in puniſhing what he will pretend a breach of truſt, ſhould in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be ready to recompence a gallant diſcharging of it: yet you ſee it is trechery &amp; cowardice to deliver up a Town to the late Kings for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, though not tenable, and upon honourable terms, in one, and yet in others to beat them and withſtand them is ſervice done againſt the King and Kingdom.</p>
            <p>He tels us in this Century, <hi>That he might end as he began, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153720:15"/>Member of the Houſe of Commons, being in all</hi> 516. <hi>are by their own order allowed</hi> 4 l. <hi>a week a man, which amounts to</hi> 110000 l. <hi>a year:</hi> This wretch knowes they never received it, unleſſe ſome few, and that in the very heat of the War, whoſe Eſtates were under the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Enemy, nay not 50. though he amplifies the number to 516. and all this he doth only to make the people believe the common Treaſure was waſted on themſelves, you may ſee then the villany of this Impoſtour.</p>
            <p>He ſets alſo this * mark before their names whó he terms, <hi>Recruiters illegally elected by the new Great Seal, the power of the Army, and voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Souldiery, and are unduly returned, and ſerve accordingly;</hi> yet when the Generall Councel of Officers in their anſwer ſay, <hi>That by the endeavours of ſome old Malignants, and by practiſes uſed in new e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, there came in a floud of Burgeſſes, that are either Malignants or Newers,</hi> then <hi>Clem</hi> is of another mind, maintains their Elections, and cryes out of breach of Privilege: Of the truth of which, we may judge by <hi>Clem,</hi> who was one of that flood, and I bleeve the top, the ſcumme for Malignancy: but if contradictons were wonders in <hi>Clems</hi> Book, he had been a greater wonder worker than <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> Hocus Pocus, or the whole gang of Sorcerers and Iuglers.</p>
            <p>But let us grant him what he ſaith, and he will marre all; for <hi>Clem, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ryane,</hi> and moſt of the ſecluded Members, who bawl at their outing, were Recruiters, how durſt they they ſit in the Houſe, or act as Members of Parliament; and what had he or <hi>Pryn</hi> to doe, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt againſt the Army for ſecluding them, who were but <hi>Milites,</hi> ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to guard the King and Houſe of Lords, as <hi>Pryn</hi> excellently of late hath found out.</p>
            <p>The Army only hindred <hi>Pryn</hi> from going to ſit among the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, whom they thought the Repreſentative of the People, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ſnarling and ranting words detein'd him a while: If he would but have deſired a Pike, and marched to guard the dore of the Houſe of Lords, he might have had it, and leave to have ſtood as long as he would. But to return to <hi>Clem,</hi> was it not rather a breach of Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege in <hi>Clem</hi> to offer to ſit, who knew he ought not, than in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to pull him out? thus you ſee he hath deſtroyed the ſtrongeſt Pillar in his whole fabrick, and removed the greateſt block of offence, nay proved that here to be the higheſt act of Iuſtice, which he eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where elſe rayls at, as the higheſt breach of Privilege, for the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153720:16"/>Army, which was raiſed to defend the Parliament, did onely free it of a multitude of intruders, yea ſuch a multitude, as overpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the reſt, were Iudges in their own cauſe, and ſo not to be voted out by a fewer. And thus you may ſee the Armies innocency, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bittereſt Enemy himſelf being Iudge.</p>
            <p>And now Gentlemen, that this Century might not be unlike the reſt of the Book, he adds lying to jugling, and ſets his mark on Mr. <hi>Blackiſton,</hi> one who was a Member from the firſt, nay he gives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the lie in the following ſcandall, and confeſſes as much; ſaying, <hi>He got himſelf returned by the Scotiſh Garriſon, Which lay there when this Parliament was ſummoned;</hi> thus you ſee he piles them three ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries high, as if he were affraid he ſhould want Room to lye in this damnable aedifice. But now to leave this, and come to his rayling.</p>
            <p>And truly Gentlemen you will gueſs, that he took the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of ſome fit of the Gout, or Stone, that he might be mad enough to rage in the compoſure of this Book, which is as very a <hi>compendium</hi> of ſnarling, without modeſty, ſence, or reaſon, as ever was compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed within the bounds of a Calves-skin: but it hath allwayes beene obſerved, that thoſe who want truth and reaſon, are accuſtomed to bluſter, in railing and falſe accuſations. Thus did old <hi>Sathan</hi> in his diſpute with <hi>Michael,</hi> thus the Heathen did aginſt the Chriſtians, the Papiſts againſt the Proteſtants, the Cabs againſt the Parliament, and thus doth <hi>Clem</hi> deal with his betters. Gentlemen, read on, and you will never wonder that Houſe is called Hell, which hath ſuch a deviliſh Landlord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clem</hi> in his Epiſtle would fain cheat us into a belief, that he railes not againſt the Body of the Houſe or the Army, when he averres, <hi>That the late King had the juſt cauſe from the beginning,</hi> calls them <hi>Rebells and Traytors, who have overthrown Religion, Laws, Liberties, and the ancient fundamentall being of Parliaments,</hi> all which the King he ſaith, <hi>took up defenſive arms to maintain.</hi> Note here, he not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gives the Parliament, but the late King too the lie, who hath in Print avowed the contrary.</p>
            <p>The Parliament in the firſt war, he ſtiles, two <hi>Juntoes, Preſbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian and Independent,</hi> who couzened, pilled, and poled the people, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming the publike Treaſure on themſelves, the Members are <hi>Iunto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Hocus Pocuſſes, State-Mountebanks,</hi> the County Committees are <hi>Zanies,</hi> and <hi>Jack-puddings</hi> with him, and all this when they were,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153720:16"/>as he is forced to confeſſe, a full and free PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>The Members choſen in after the firſt War, he ſtiles <hi>Recruiters,</hi> who were illegally elected, unduly returned, and ſerved accordingly, <hi>Clem</hi> was one of theſe, and ſo meaſures their Corne by his owne Buſhell.</p>
            <p>The preſent Parliament he calls <hi>Col.</hi> Prides <hi>Dray horſes, Trayters, Tyrants, Thieves, Col</hi> Prides <hi>Parliament, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Councel of State he calls, <hi>A pack of forty Knaves;</hi> this for the generall; beſides he hath a bout with every Member almoſt in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</p>
            <p>The Lord Gen. <hi>Eſſex,</hi> a man as mild as gallant, and whoſe onely fault was, that he was too eaſie to believe (as many honeſt and noble ſoules are) yet with <hi>Clem</hi> forſooth, he was a man ſtubbornly ſtout; and why pray? becauſe he would not runne away, or let the Cabs beat him; you ſee how <hi>Clem</hi> was for the Parliament; can any man i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine that this Wretch did not accuſe Colonell <hi>Fiennes</hi> out of deſign, and draw his purblinde Brother in, merely to helpe to bark?</p>
            <p>The Lord Generall <hi>Fairfax,</hi> a man whoſe Fame rings through all <hi>Europe,</hi> whoſe matchleſſe deeds will hardly be believed by poſterity; a man who exceeded his Enemies as farre in fidelity and clemency, as in valour and fortune; whoſe mercifull granting, and inviolable keeping of Articles, begat admiration in the foes, and repining in ſome harſher ſpirited friends; who commonly conquered the Foe double, their bodyes by his magnanimity, and their affections by his clemency, and whoſe name ſounded among the healths of the moſt inveterate Cavaliers, finally, a man whoſe humility is as unparral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd as all the reſt, who is as farre from being elevated by his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, as he was from being dejected in the greateſt diſtreſſe; yet with this Fellow he is a man of a Brutiſh valour, a Brutiſh Generall, a Brute, a Foole, &amp;c. But to the name of <hi>Fairfax</hi> ſhall be erected Trophies on the higheſt Pinacles of Fame, when this bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Fellowes memory, ſhall ſtinke in the noſtrills of all honeſt men.</p>
            <p>The Lord Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> a man whoſe virgin Fortune never yet was forced, upon whoſe Conquering Enſignes plumed victory hath alwaies perch'd; a man as prudent as valiant, and as pious as prudent, who in all his high ſucceſſes ever gives all the glory to God,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153720:17"/>attributing all to the prayers of Gods people, nothing to the valout of his unconquered Troops, accounting it his higheſt glory to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed as the meaneſt inſtrument in the hand of God; in fine, a man who hath wholly devoted himſelf to the ſervice of God, and his Country, never refuſing any perill or trouble, hazard or travaile, which the defence of Religion, and his Countries freedome calleth him unto: yet is this man ſo rail'd at by this Fellow, and ſuch heaps of dirt thrown at him, that had I impudence enough to defile my pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per with them, yet I could not finde room enough in a narrow diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to inſert them, every page being beſpotted with the railings, and curſings of this <hi>Shimei,</hi> againſt that Worthy. But the deeds of <hi>Cromwell</hi> praiſe him in the Gates; when he ſitteth among the Elders of the Land, <hi>England</hi> ariſeth up, and calls him bleſſed, <hi>Ireland</hi> alſo and <hi>Scotland</hi> praiſe him, unto whom God hath made him an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Deliverance.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Henry Vane ſenior,</hi> he ſtiles, <hi>The Old Dogge,</hi> judge O Reader, who barks and ſnarles. Sir <hi>Henry Vane junior, A Whelp of the old curre;</hi> let him carry the title who is the bawling Puppie. Mr. <hi>Gurdon, a fellow that ſpits venome as natu ally as a Toad;</hi> what a venemous Beaſt is <hi>Clem</hi> then? Mr. <hi>Holland, originally a Link Boy;</hi> a new pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digree indeed, a very piece of Non-ſence. Sir <hi>Hexry Mildmay, a Procuror, Pimpe,</hi> and <hi>Pander;</hi> He had deſerved the Name, would he have Pimp't for the luſt of a King, or betraid his Mother (his Countrey) to be abuſed by him, as <hi>Clem</hi> hath. <hi>Mr.</hi> Rowſe, <hi>the il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>literate Jew of</hi> Eaton College; had this fellow been ſo much a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian or Scholar, as that grave Gentleman, he would never have plaid the Knave and Foole ſo in print. Indeed I believe he is not a man of his reading, for I never found any thing ſtoln out of a <hi>Prag.</hi> or <hi>Man in the Moon</hi> in his writings. Sir <hi>Hardreſſe Waller, the one-eyed</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyphemus <hi>of Paſtbord;</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Clem</hi> and his Gang, going to adjourn in truth diſſolve the Parliament that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning they were outed.</note> he could ſee to catch this <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> when he was going to rob us of our <hi>Palladium,</hi> and ſteal that, upon which depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Fortune of <hi>Englands</hi> Liberties. Sir <hi>Thomas Wroth, Jack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudd ng to</hi> Prideaux <hi>the Poſtmaſter;</hi> There is never a Iack-pudding to an <hi>Aulicus,</hi> if <hi>Clem</hi> be not, who hath out-ly'd, out-rail'd, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlander'd him, and all the reſt to boot, and ſo over-acted them, that the other Hell can never ſhew one may match him. Mr. Corbet, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitor Generall, The Prologue to the Hangman who looks more like a Hangman, than the Hangman himſelfe;</hi> but let thoſe judge, who
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153720:17"/>have ſeen both, which looks more like a Hangman: ſure <hi>Clem</hi> never ſaw his own face in a true Glaſſe. All this <hi>Clem</hi> hath done, and yet this Brazen face dares to averre, that the witneſſe againſt him, for but ſaying, <hi>The Gentleman was a leane meager man,</hi> by the incivility of his words was a man of no breeding, what ſhall we judge of <hi>Clem</hi> then?</p>
            <p>Of the Iudges he ſaith, <hi>That true men may go to the Gallowes, Theeves muſt ſit upon the Bench; Clem</hi> will be afore hand with them, becauſe he fears they will end with him: I ſay, <hi>Gallowes claim thy due.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The City, even that generous City of <hi>London,</hi> which hath expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo much bloud and treaſure in defence of their Freedome, he cals, <hi>That Dull Beaſt:</hi> it would not anſwer to <hi>Clems</hi> ſpurre, but ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Army to unhorſe him, and the reſt of his fellow ranke Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>Of the Clergy in generall he ſaith, <hi>The Clergy in all times and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ever held with the mighty</hi> (I am ſure he holds not with the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty) <hi>as the</hi> Iaccho <hi>hunts with the</hi> Lyon <hi>to partake of his prey. The Clergy nave ever had an itching to be medling with State-affairs, which ſhewes how contemptible an opinion they have of their own coat, that they can finde no contentment in it, and yet they would have the Laity to have a reverend opinion of it; but univerſall experience teacheth us, how mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable that Commonwealth is, where the corruption of a Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, proves the generation of a Stateſ-man;</hi> and ſo it did the Army, how miſerable ours was, where the corruption of a Parliament man, proved the generation of a Cavalier, which cauſed <hi>Clems</hi> outing. But I will leave theſe things to our Clergy-men to anſwer, who I hope will confute him in deed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Popiſh Clergy,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>draw all publique affairs under their juriſdiction,</hi> quatenus <hi>there is</hi> peccatum; <hi>the Presbyterian,</hi> quatenus <hi>there is</hi> ſcandalum, <hi>in all humane actions; and the Independents are a compoſition of</hi> Chriſtian, Iew, Turke, <hi>as</hi> Mahomets Alchoran <hi>was a Galli naufrey of</hi> Iew <hi>and</hi> Chriſtian: truly <hi>Clems</hi> is of <hi>Jew. Turke,</hi> and <hi>Heathen,</hi> and <hi>Clem,</hi> believe it, is no Independent, for there is not one dramme of Chriſtian in his Compoſition.</p>
            <p>But the Epiſcopall good <hi>Ontaſes,</hi> they (hold <hi>Clem</hi> did not our Magpies prey with Eagles, nay and perch above them too, nay and in <hi>Norwich</hi> not many years agoe, was ſeen a <hi>Wren</hi> on the Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litan
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153720:18"/>Magpies, and the Magpie on the Eagles back ſoaring to an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable lofty pitch) they meddle with nothing. <hi>Clem</hi> could be drunk over night, rayle, lye, ſlander, and grind his Neighbour, and yet have the Sacrament next morning (ſtay, now I think on't, I dare ſay for love of <hi>Clem</hi> his brother writ that learned piece with Marginall Notes to it, to prove the Sacrament a converting Ordinance) nay and might dance about the May-pole, or be drunk again in the afternoon; for a baudy Court or ſo, alas it was but paying a monethly tax to it's Officers, and he could keep a VVench or two for all the Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens; (yet how doth <hi>Clem</hi> pine at a monethly tax now, why <hi>Clem,</hi> Liberty and Lechery, begin both with one Letter.) It may be a Biſhop was a Lord Keeper or Treaſurer, and he being unmarried, would fell juſtice and places cheaper than Lay-men, which was a great eaſe to <hi>Clems</hi> tender Conſcience: beſides thoſe good <hi>Oniaſes,</hi> never diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Athieſticall prophane fellowes; Had old <hi>Clem</hi> lived from <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> the Monks time, to little <hi>Lands,</hi> I would have warranted him from their courts (paying his tax abovecited I mean.) It was a Puritan, a man who had ſome fear of God, delight in his Ordinances, and a little too much Conſcience than to become a Proteſtant at large, <hi>id eſt,</hi> a Papiſt Royall, one who owed no duty to any, but ſlavery to his King of his outward, to the Patriarck of <hi>Canterbury</hi> of his inward man, (and what was this to <hi>Clem?</hi>) who ſtuck in the Prelats ſtomacks; yet <hi>Clem</hi> whilſt your mind runs ſo on your good <hi>Oniaſes,</hi> remember a little the Covenant, but what is an Oath to a Cavaleer, eſpecially an old one.</p>
            <p>Of the Aſſembly, he ſaith, <hi>The Houſes aboliſh as ſuperſtitious, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe legall, the Convocation of Learned Divines</hi> (they are learned and Divines who even now in all ages were <hi>Iaccho's</hi> in practiſe at leaſt) <hi>regularly ſummoned by the Kings Writ, and duely elected by the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy: and the Houſe of Commons nominates an Aſſembly of Gifted Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> (who would think an old fellow, who hath got ſo much money by an Office in the Exchequor, would think the worſe of gifted men) <hi>indeed Wicked</hi> Simons <hi>who ſlander the Godly</hi> Onias <hi>to out him of his Prieſts place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This old piece of Apocrypha railes at the Houſes, though by his Confeſſion a full and free Parliament, and for whoſe ſervice he ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured and ſpent ſo, yet he neither lyes, nor changes his Principles. Then at all the Aſſembly men, who were the learnedſt of all parties;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153720:18"/>and laſtly knits up with a notorious lye, that the Houſe of Commons nominated, that is, <hi>onely,</hi> when the Lords he knows nominated pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably to the Commons.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>They daub up all with the untempered Mortar of hypocriſie by their Rabbies of the Aſſembly;</hi> This <hi>Iew</hi> may live long enough and write too, before he will deſerve the Title of <hi>Rabbi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But his fury ceaſes not here, all Miniſters that ever were for the Parliament, muſt come under old Laſhers whip: He calls them <hi>'Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit-Devills,</hi> who transformed themſelves into Angels of Light; <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit Inceudiaries,</hi> with whom had an Order been taken from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, they had never kindled a War between the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they curſt <hi>Meroz</hi> and <hi>neutrality</hi> ſo long, till they brought Gods curſe on the Land, and put both Church and Common wealth into a flame. You Gentlemen have a care, you ſee if the Pretender ſhould get in, upon whom the Cabs will lay the Load, if you ſhould pray or Plot him in, I beleeve you will hardly have any ſinging daies unleſſe at the Gallowes.</p>
            <p>Nay his malice paſſes <hi>Tweed.</hi> The Kirk or General Aſſembly of <hi>Scotland,</hi> he calls, <hi>a few ambitious pedanticall Churchmen; The Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> (whom ſometimes he would ſeem to claw, yet his malice is ſo great he cannot hold now but he muſt ſcratch) <hi>he calls Clergy-Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtors, Zealots, imployed by</hi> Argyle, <hi>to aſperſe thoſe that did oppoſe him, as if they were fallen from their firſt love, turned Enemies to the cauſe of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>had with</hi> Demas <hi>embraced this preſent World, with many more jeers and revilings caſt upon them, the Mar<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> of</hi> Argyle, <hi>and all the Presbyterian party, together with prayſes conferred on</hi> Hamilton, Montroſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And this is all the Kirk will get, by dandling the Royall Babie on her knees; to wit, to have her eyes ſcratch'd out by it and it's play-fellows, when they are high enough to reach Her.</p>
            <p>And now as if it were beneath him onely to lye, ſay and un-ſay, ſlander and revile, he adds blaſphemy, and abuſing of Sacred VVrit, to fill up the meaſure of his iniquity, Thus ſaith this wretch; <hi>God bleſſe all honeſt men from the light of</hi> Olivers <hi>countenance.</hi> Again, <hi>At last, the Spirit of the Lord called up</hi> Oliver Cromwell, <hi>who ſtanding a good while, with lifted up eyes, as it were in a Trance, &amp; his neck a little enclining to one fide, as if he expected</hi> Mahomets <hi>Dove to deſcend, and whiſper in his Ear</hi> (foh! this ſmels of the Character of a <hi>London</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urnall,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153720:19"/>what <hi>Clem</hi> doſt thou make no more conſcience of robbing the Cabs of this jeſts, than honeſt men of their good names?) <hi>and ſending forth abundantly the greans of the ſpirit</hi> (who can but groan to heare this) <hi>ſpent an hour in Prayer. and an hour and an halfe in a Sermon;</hi> more time than <hi>Clems</hi> Godly <hi>Oniaſes</hi> ſpent in thoſe Dutyes in a yeare.</p>
            <p>From thus abuſing the Spirit, he falls upon the Saints, and this wretch who calls the keeping a Guard in the lower part of <hi>Pauls</hi> (a place never employed in any religious performance, and where the baudy, and ſuch like Courts were kept) <hi>a making the Houſe of God, a Den of Theeves;</hi> here dares defile the living Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, the Saints, endeavouring to render that glorious title, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God hath honoured his Elect, abominable in the eyes of the people.</p>
            <p>Thus he ſaith: <hi>The Knaves lyed like Saints; it is a particular pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege for the Saints to lie without ſin, or at leaſt without imputation of ſin; Alchimie Saints, trayterous, tyrannous, theeviſh Saints, Reprobate Saints</hi> (beware Hornes, a Bull a Bull) <hi>Bloody cheating Saints, though this br Godly nnd Saint-like dealing, yet this is not plain nor fair dealing. Theſe are the acts of the Godly, to make innocency it ſelf ſeem nocent, if all ſhould be ſelf-denying men, there would be few Godly men left in the houſe. The Godly Gang, Godly cut-throats, Canniball Saints,</hi> with much more which I omit.</p>
            <p>Now it can be no excuſe for this wretch, to ſay he means ſuch as on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtile themſelves Saints; For, ſuppoſe a crafty man ſhould deſire to cloath his black deeds with that white rayment, therefore muſt he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file it? his Bible teaches him not to rayl at, and abuſe Angels of light, becauſe the Devill ſometimes aſſumes their ſhape; or to worry ſheep, becauſe ravening woolves creep in their cloathing: But behold this wretch dares defie the very name of Saint, as if holineſs were a crime. Take heed, O <hi>Belzebub,</hi> leſt he get the Lordſhip of thy Hell too, and be preferred to command in chief, as being the more daring Fiend.</p>
            <p>In fine, he ſumms himſelf up, and gives an epitome of his vilanous tenents in this inſuing piece, <hi>viz. I do hereby declare, and proteſt before that God that made me a man, and not a beaſt</hi> (and therefore you will make your ſelf one) <hi>a freeman, and not a ſlave; That if any man what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, that taketh upon him the reverend name &amp; title of a Judg or Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, ſhall give ſentence upon this, or any other act of this piece of a Houſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153720:19"/>of Commons, I will, &amp; lawfully may, the inſlaving ſcar-crow doctrine of all time-ſerving, State-flattering Prieſts, &amp; Miniſters notwithſtanding follow the examples of</hi> Sampſon, Iudith, Iaell, <hi>and</hi> Ehud, <hi>and by ponyard, piſtol, poiſon, or any other means whatſoever, ſecret or open, proſecute to the death the ſaid Iudge, and uſtice, and all their principall abbettors: and I do hereby exvite, and exhort all generous freeborn Engliſhmen to the like reſolutions, and to enter into leagues defenſive, and offenſive, and Sacramentall aſſociations, ſeven or eight, or as many as can confide in one another, to defend and revenge mutually one anothers perſons, lives, lambs, and liberties as aforeſaid, against this, and all other illegall, and tyrannous uſurpations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is this the voice of a man, a Chriſtian, a Proteſtant? what ſpirit called up <hi>Clem</hi> to preach this ſtuffe? yet give me leave to repeat it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His text is the late Act declaring what ſhall be Treaſon, which he wreſts horribly, and falſly gloſſes upon; endeavouring to make the world beleeve, That there was never ſuch a prodigious act, which makes our words and thoughts Treaſon, which were free alwaies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Monarchy. But <hi>Clem,</hi> where is there any word in that Act, which layes hold on thought, for words, was there no ſpeaking Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nay and thinking too under Monarchy? what think you of this caſe in Law, That a man for telling another, <hi>He dream't he had kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the King,</hi> ſhall be accounted a Traytor: nay, the reaſon of this Law confirmes it more, for beſide that, it will be adjudged, <hi>that he might pretend a Dream, to feel the other, and ſo draw him in;</hi> it is plainly affirmed, that the Law muſt ſuppoſe he would not have drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſo, unleſſe his thoughts had run upon it awake. To omit all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, take but two ſtories recorded in our Chronicles, which will ſhew how free words and thoughts were, under Monarchy. One <hi>Walker,</hi> which was Landlord of the Crown in Cheap-ſide, as you are of <hi>Hell</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> for but merrily ſaying, when his Child was commended, <hi>That if he would be a good Boy, he ſhould be Heire to the crown one day,</hi> was condemned and ſuffered as a Traytor. And Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire <hi>Burdet</hi> of <hi>Arrow</hi> in <hi>Warwickshire,</hi> for ſaying, <hi>would the head were in his belly, that perſwaded the King to kill that White-Buck,</hi> was condemned, drawn from the Tower to Tyborn, and beheaded; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and bluſh then, if thou canſt <hi>Clem,</hi> how free our words were under Monarchy.</p>
            <p>His doctrine drawn from this, is <hi>That a man may, and he will, ſtab,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153720:20"/>&amp;c. any illegall tyrannous uſurper, or his abbettors,</hi> that is, any man that he pleaſes to ſtile ſo. Is not this more devilliſh than the doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines of the Aſſaſſinates, or their followers, the Ieſuitical Papiſts. By his, a private Rogue, that can pretend nothing whereby any power is derived to him, may murder any man: by theirs, the party to be murdered, muſt firſt have ſentence paſt againſt him by the Pope, or the ſuperiour, and then ſome one is appointed by them, who hath a diſpenſation, and an holy inſtrument conſecrated to boot, to perform it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He anſwers all objections, by reviling the objectors; calling all thoſe learned men, Proteſtants or Papiſts, who have oppoſed ſuch murderous tenents, and confuted them out of the word of God, law of nature and reaſon, <hi>Time-ſerving, State-flattering Prieſts, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. His Scriptures to prove it, are the examples of <hi>Ehud, Jael,</hi> and <hi>Sampſon,</hi> all which have been ſo largely and learnedly anſwered by Learned men, both Proteſtants and Papiſts, that it is needieſſe to mention it here, had we room for ſo large a controverſie: yet ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that <hi>Clem</hi> holds, <hi>That he or his Gang, when they liſt to murder any man, have an immediate call from Heaven to do it;</hi> who hath the ſpirit of <hi>Iack of Leiden</hi> doubled upon him now?</p>
            <p>For <hi>Iudith,</hi> I could not find her act in my Bible, and ſo, I conceive ſhe and <hi>Clems Onias,</hi> were appochryphal Cozens, but ſearching, I found, <hi>Vengeance is mine, I will repay ſaith the Lord:</hi> and I humbly conceive, neither the Prophet who writ it, nor the Apoſtle who quotes it, were <hi>time-ſerving, State flattering Prieſts and Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. His Application is to exhort and invite all <hi>Engliſh</hi> men to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this his Doctrine; and truly ſome Vilains, both <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scots,</hi> have put it in practice, as the murders of Doctor <hi>Doriſlaus,</hi> and M. <hi>Aſcham</hi> teſtifie, which though <hi>Clem</hi> may approve, yet I am conſident no honeſt or gallant man but abhors.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And that they might do it effectually, he preſcribes them means to do it, to wit, <hi>by entring into leagues and ſacramentall aſſociations:</hi> yet <hi>Clem</hi> forgot to teach them where they might get a Father <hi>Garnet,</hi> a Prieſt to adminiſter it, for ſure none but one in holy Order can be fit for a Cabb.</p>
            <p>And now truly, ſeeing <hi>Clem</hi> hath been ſo ready to help forward murders, by my conſent the Parliament ſhould make him a means to prevent or deterre his Diſciples, by hanging up according to their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153720:20"/>Act this great Doctor of the Aſſaſſinates, the next aſſaſſination that is perpetrated; and ſo fare well to him. —</p>
            <p>For I ſhall now come to his deſigne, having ſhewn the manner of his carrying it on, which is to render the parliament cauſe unjuſt, and them odious to the world, and to performe this he</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt enumerates many errors and miſcarriages in them, in their carrying on their Cauſe: but ſhould we grant all he ſaith, though more than is true abundantly enough, yet cannot the miſcarriage in the inſtrument, render the Cauſe unjuſt, unleſſe it be ſo in it ſelfe; which that it was not, he himſelfe confeſſes in this book, where he affirms <hi>The cavaliers fought for Regall Tyranny,</hi> ſtiles their oppoſers, <hi>the well-affected,</hi> tels us, <hi>The conteſt was between the Kings Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and the Peoples Laws and Liberties;</hi> profeſſes <hi>he had ſerved his Country faithfully in ſerving them, and accounts it his honour ſo to have done:</hi> Now therefore all his ſtuffe makes againſt himſelf, and for the Army, juſtifying what the Army charged them with, to wit, <hi>Breach of Truſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Another thing is, <hi>by urging the Oaths of Allegiance, Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and Covenant;</hi> but for this read a ſhort diſcourſe, entituled <hi>A diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engaged ſurvey of the Engagement,</hi> where this is ſo excellently hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, that nothing need be added to covince him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The other is <hi>The ſecluding the Members,</hi> and concerning this, becauſe upon this hinge the whole controverſie turns, I ſhal endeavor your ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>This PARLIAMENT being ſenſible of the tyranny, oppreſſion, and ſtubborn reſolutions to continue them in the late King, together with the encroachment of Him, and ſome of His Predeceſſors, upon their Privileges and our Liberties, were reſolved to vindicate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive both their owne Authority and our Freedoms. In order here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, they claim their right of the diſpoſal of the MILITIA, and diſclaime the wrong uſurpation of a NEGATIVE VOICE in him; and this to render him unable to raiſe commotions, or hinder juſt and neceſſary Lawes; for they knew by often tryal, of his breach of Truſt, Promiſe and Oath, that it would be impoſſible to have Him good, unleſſe they made it impoſſible for him to do miſchief.</p>
            <p>He on the other ſide was as buſie, endeavouring by all the Clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtine Plots and conſpiracies He could to ruine them, and in them the Power of PARLIAMENTS, and Freedome of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153720:21"/>but when He ſaw this would not doe; but that they grew daily deeper rooted in the peoples affection, He reſolved to caſt the utmoſt chance, and by fine force to oppreſſe them.</p>
            <p>Hereupon fears and Tumults are pretended that He might with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, and being got out of Town, with His eldeſt ſon, He hies to <hi>York,</hi> where nothing was left undone, either by Declarations and Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in publique, promiſes and flatteries in private, to draw away the People, the Queen, and Crown Iewels being packt into <hi>Holland,</hi> to provide money, arms, and ammunition.</p>
            <p>Vpon this, growing confident of His power, He proclaims the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and their adhaerents, Traytors and Rebels, ſets up His Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard againſt them, and then that He might ſeem to deſire peace, ſends a Meſſage for a Treaty.</p>
            <p>The PARLIAMENT Anſwer, <hi>That He had done that which never any evill Councell produced in former times, or any age ſeen; that he had declared a Parliaments actions treaſonable, and their perſons Traitors, and thereupon had ſet up His Standard againſt them, whereby He had put the Parliament, and in them the whole Nation out of His protection; and that untill His Standard was taken down, and thoſe Declarations and Proclamations were recalled, He had put them in ſuch a condition, that whilſt they ſo remain'd, they could not, by the fundamentall Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges of Parliament, the publike truſt repoſed in them, or with the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall good, or ſafety of this Nation, give Him any other anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus to fighting they fall, &amp; He, after he had murderd many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and rob'd and plunder'd moſt parts, is beaten and taken Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive. The Parliament upon a charitable conceit that He might be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, His evil Counſellors being removed, ſend Him Propoſitions again and again, which are ſtill refuſed: The Army alſo, whilſt in their cuſtody, dealt with Him by all perſwaſive means, giving Him more liberty of converſe, yet all to no purpoſe. Whereupon, The PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAMENT finding Him the evill Counſellor, a ſetled and obſtinate Tyrant, Vote <hi>No more addreſſes to Him,</hi> and Declare, <hi>They will ſettle the Nation without Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But He having taken advantage of the Liberty allowed Him, had ſo ſown His tares, and ſcattered His Commiſſions, that there ſprung up a ſecond War on all parts, in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales, Scotland</hi> alſo by the conſent of their Parliament, under the conduct of <hi>Hamilton</hi> brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in upon us, contrary to the large Treaty, and their ſo pretended<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153720:21"/>eſteemed Covenant; hereupon many of the moſt reſolute Lords and Gentlemen, being abroad upon imployment, the Parliament being laid at by Petitions, which his favorers every where promoted, ſome for feare, others for favour, and a third ſort for envy, recalled their Vote, and appoint another Treaty; their good Lordſhips all this while refuſing to delare <hi>Hamilton</hi> a Traytor, and his Army Enemies, whom the Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi> had ſentenced as the violaters of the large Treaty and Covenant, the breach being ſo apparent, and their party beſide having not the managing of it in chief.</p>
            <p>At length God having ſubdued the Enemy, by his bleſſing the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of the Army, which he owned every where in an eſpeciall manner, and the King refuſing this laſt time to grant the Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; The Army being ſenſible, as being eye-witneſſes of the miſeries and ſlaughters brought upon their Country daily for the Intereſt of one man, who had out-lawed himſelf, and forfeited his Crown, Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Parliament to ſtand to their former Vote, and ſettle the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without Him; but finding that there was a great part, moſt, if not all the Lords, and many Commons, who had not only betrayed their Truſt, but would alſo betray their Countrey, and deliver up all the honeſt party into the hands of an enraged Enemy, they reſolve to bring their aſſiſtance to them which ſtood faithfull to that cauſe, for which they were raiſed, and ſworn to defend, and ſo ſecluded ſome who were moſt active for Him.</p>
            <p>And now I deſire to know what breach of Privilege this could be to exclude the Houſe, ſuch who (by the judgment of the parliament,<note place="margin">As in the Anſwer <hi>August</hi> 1642 fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears.</note> and that paſſed in the ſight of God and men) had contrary to the fundamentall Privileges of Parliament, the publike truſt repoſed in them, and the generall good and ſafety of the Nation, not only trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with, but voted his denyall of their Propoſitions <hi>a ground for Peace,</hi> who had his Standard up then in the Revolted ſhips, and in <hi>Ireland</hi> againſt them, whereby they were Traytors and Rebels in his thoughts &amp; actions too, &amp; in an incapacity to treat by their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, could not oblige him to keep any thing had he granted it, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially he being in <hi>dureſs</hi> under reſtraint, as he did imply in one of his laſt meſſages?</p>
            <p>But ſhould you ask by what lawfull authority the Army could call them to account, who were their ſuperiours, and how without breach of privilege, exclude them?</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:153720:22"/>
            <p>I ſhall thus anſwer. In all actions the end is the chief, and moſt deſirable, but the means only as they tend to the attaining it are to be eſteemed and exerciſed: the end is the generall good, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the Liberties and Freedome of the people; to attain this end Parliaments were inſtituted as the moſt apt means by our wiſe Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors; and to preſerve theſe meanes, and by theſe the end, endued with many and high privileges, that ſo thoſe high Courts being invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable, they might without fear diſcharge their high Truſt. Now in this cauſe we were (and all good men alſo ought in all times to be) engaged to preſerve this Parliament and it's Privileges, in order to the common good, and when this could not be done but by our ſwords, we engaged to draw them: among us were many rotten Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, which endeavoured to deſtroy the publike weal of the body po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick, to cut off theſe which were uncurable by any other remedy, this Army was raiſed, according to that golden rule</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Immedicabile vulnus</l>
               <l>Enſe recidendum eſt ne pars ſyncera trahatur;</l>
            </q>
            <p>and they lopt off many of the firſt and palpable infected ones, yet ſome remaining they did infect others, and that ſo dangerouſly, that unleſſe they were cut off, the whole body was in apparent danger; now none could do this but the Army, which were the Surgeons, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for ſuch actions; they did it as they ought to do, it being their proper work: for the excluded Members relying upon their number, did act contrary to their truſt, our Liberties, and the fundamental pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges of Parliament; how then can any ſuperſtructory Privilege be pleaded by or for them, who had not only ruin'd the fundamentall ones, but were fully bent to deſtroy this Parliament, upon whoſe good or bad ſucceſs the very being of Parliaments did depend, as upon them the Liberties and freedome of the people? for that morning they were excluded, they went with a reſolution to adjourn the Parliament for a long time, which act, in that unſetled time, muſt have proved an ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſſolution, and of this the Army were certainly and fully infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and by Gods goodneſſe had three dayes time to conſult what to doe, which had the others not given them, they might in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity have brought that wicked deſign to paſſe before they could have been informed or reſolved. Let glory be given therefore to that God, who, and who alone was able to turne the Councell of thoſe <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitophels</hi> into folly, yea to their own deſtruction; and let wretches
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:153720:22"/>jeer at providence which hath ſo oft confounded them.</p>
            <p>And now what rationall man but wil ſmile to hear men plead Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary privilege, to protect them in deſtroying a Parliament? as if fences which were made to keep Hogs out of Corn, ought to be uſed only in defending them from the Maſtives when gotten in, that ſo they might root up and deſtroy all? The Army therefore (in my judgment) are ſo farre from breach of Covenant, and duty in this act, that I ſhall conclude, They had broke both had they not done it: for they were bound by duty, and covenanted to maintaine the Liberties and freedom of the people, and the privileges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and this they could never have performed by ſuffering an apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate Faction in Parliament to deſtroy the Parliament, upon which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended both Parliament privilege, and <hi>Engliſh</hi> freedom. Let then all who are faithfull to their Countrey and Covenant, eccho out an <hi>Enge</hi> to this act, though blind and purblind wretches have decryed it with an <hi>Apage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This for breach of Privilege, for the other, <hi>By what Law they did it?</hi> I anſwer, by the ſame Law by which they were raiſed, and before continually acted, even by Authority of Parliament, to defend our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and in order to them this Parliament, againſt all that ſhould go about to overthrow them and deſtroy this; for it being apparent that the Enemies had appealed to the Sword, force was ordered to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and ſubdue them: unleſſe then the power of Parliament be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed lawfull, or it be proved that the Army had no ſuch power deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to them, which can never be done, the Generals Commiſſion, and Parliaments Ordinance evincing the contrary, it muſt be yeelded That they had a particular Law for what they did, beſides the general of Common-ſafety.</p>
            <p>But had they had none, yet you may conſider Neceſſity hath no Law, and that there was no other gentler remedie left them, appeares before, by which they might hinder the diſſolution of the Parliament, and deſtruction of that cauſe they were bound to preſerve, even with the death of all oppoſers.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, had all particular written Lawes been againſt them, yet were theſe to give place and bow, when common ſafety doth enter and aſcend the Throne, under penalty of breaking natures and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons high and juſt Oath of Supremacy, confirmed alſo to Engliſhmen by many maxims of their written Lawes; as</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:153720:23"/>
            <p n="1">1. The Generall inconvenience is more to be regarded in Law, than a particular miſchief; if then any particular Law muſt give place with a miſchiefe, to prevent a generall inconvenience, it will much more follow, that the ſame muſt be done to prevent a generall miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and what miſchief could be greater or more generall than uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall ſlavery, and remedileſſe bondage? and it is the greateſt reaſon that particular Lawes ſhould be diſpenſed with on this ground; for they ſubſiſt but in order to the generall good, and are made by Men to that end, which yet being but men can only provide for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but cannot foreknow enſuing inconveniences.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whatſoever written Law contradicteth the Law of God, nature and reaſon, it is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> void. Now as all men are commanded to defend their Countryes, and their own freedom by all theſe, for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they ſhould they would ſinne againſt their very Creation; ſo eſpecially we Engliſhmen, who beſides theſe generall ties, have the Oath of God (as ſome term it, who I fear make uſe of it only for the God of this world their own gaine) the Covenant, and other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements obliging us to this duty, but moſt of al the Army, who had a particular cal to this work out of the many thouſands of our <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I hope, I have given ſome ſatisfaction concerning this point, I ſhall endeavour the ſame in anſwering other objections.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1:</label> 
               <hi>It may be objected, that we argue</hi> ex falſo ſuppoſito, <hi>and falſely ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that they had forfeited their truſt; and that the late King intended to deſtroy our Liberties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>
               </label> I ſhall begin with the latter clauſe; That this was the Kings inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be proved by an undenyable argument, drawn from experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his former and latter doings; nay he was ſo far from not inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it, that he ſcorn'd to promiſe or grant them to us. He I ſay who neither regarded his Grants, Promiſes, or Oathes in former Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, who when he ſeemed moſt to comply, and paſt the beſt Bills openly this Parliament, then had the moſt dangerous privat plots to ruine the Parliament, as the deſign of the <hi>Engliſh, French, Scotch,</hi> and <hi>Irish</hi> Armies diſcovered, and confeſt by his owne Inſtruments, and printed at large will ſhew; yet now at laſt though he had the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of dureſſe, reſtraint, and lying under a force to evade all, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all, he was ſo aſſured of his good vaſſals in both Houſes: can any think that he who (to omit his former tyrannies which require a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumne) dared to proclaime a Parliament Traytors, ſet up a ſtandard
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153720:23"/>againſt them, ſpoyle, rob, and murder three Nations, and when bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and captiv'd deny their juſt Propoſitions, had he had power durſt not have done any thing?</p>
            <p>For their forfeiture of truſt their own words prove it, for they ttea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with him, though he had not taken down his Standard, nor recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Declarations, wherein they, and in them the whole Nation were declared Traytors.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>But then</hi> ſays one; <hi>had all the Parliament, yea the Army it ſelf, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited theirs, who did the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>
               </label> For this I have ſaid ſomething before, as that a charitable conceit that he might change, his evill Counſell being removed, cauſed them to trye, as alſo to ſhew the world how unwilling they were to take the forfeiture, if he would give any reaſonable ſatisfaction; but there is a vaſt difference between the others proceedings, theſe as if a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Nation had been but things for a Tyrant to trample on, as if Oaths bound them, but not Him, as if they might be Traytors, He could not, when He would not yeeld, yet Voted we muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with what he would be pleaſed to grant; &amp; as if all the bloud and treaſure had been ſpent only to terrifie the people, for daring to ſtand by a Parliament for the future, yet he muſt have that at laſt yeelded to him when beaten, which we could but have loſt had he been an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Conqueror, and all to ſhew the ſlavery of his good Vaſſals the Lords and Commons.</p>
            <p>Thus you may ſee one partie departed not from their right but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Courteſie made him a tender again of his Crowne, conſidering He was but a man, and that wilfull and ſtubborn, and had been educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in ſuch principles, that he even ſucked in Tyranny with his milke, and hoping that the judgement of God, to whom he had appealed, by warre given againſt him, and good Counſellers, about him, might have ſoftened his Heart.</p>
            <p>The other did, and would have the ſupreme Court and whole nation as ſtrictly bound, as if he had never cut the tye in ſunder, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good what the Cavaliers did but aim at, <hi>That a King was above Law, and accountable to none but God,</hi> both which they before at leaſt ſeem'd to deny, and then pray what were they, and all that took part with them leſſe than Rebels and Traytors? and ſo we had not onely bin delivered into the hands of an exaſperated enemy fleſhd in blood, but the power of Parliaments for ever deſtroyed, and <hi>William Pryns</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:153720:24"/>Book too for ought I can ſee to the contrary might have been burnt under his noſe, intituled <hi>The Soveraign power of Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>3</label> Again, They will object, <hi>That if theſe men, being the greateſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Houſe, had forfeited their truſt, how comes it to paſſe we have a Parliament? for the major part ſtands for the whole, and ſo the whole hath forfeited.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> To this thus, not to runne farre and ſtop a margent with quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as <hi>Pryn</hi> hath done, who maintains, That the minor part ſtanding firm to their truſt are the Parliament, and the major doing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary a faction, and brings the judgment of a Parliament, to confirme this, in the time of <hi>Richard</hi> 2. paſſed upon ſuch a party, cajoled by that King and <hi>Buſhie</hi> the Speaker, nor to paſſe <hi>Tweed,</hi> and ſhew you that it is the ſame caſe now in <hi>Scotland,</hi> concerning the <hi>Hamiltonian</hi> faction in the late Invaſion; I ſhall only inſtance in this Parliament. The King, and Major part of Lords, beſides the Biſhops themſelves, were againſt the outing the Biſhops: here were two Eſtates, then having not forfeited their Truſt, againſt the Commons, ſome of which too were Epiſcoparians: yet the generall good requiring their outing the nice puntilio's of Privilege was laid aſide, and that Bill preſt the fifth time by the Commons, backt by the People, and had been the fiftieth time, had it not been paſſed: for all they cryed out that it was un-Parliamentarie, and a breach of Privilege to offer the ſame Bill twice the ſame Seſſion. In our caſe there was but a part of the Commons acting againſt the generall good, a part for it, and ſo great a part as are declared enough to make a Parliament, being farre above forty; and for what reaſon could ſuch a Law be made, but to provide in ſuch a caſe, that if all the reſt ſhould neglect or deſert their duty, yet forty ſtanding faſt, might ſave their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>
               </label> But it may be asked, <hi>by what Law the Houſe of Lords could be laid aſide by the Commons?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> By the ſame Law, which is the Supreme Law, the generall good. For conſider of what uſe that Houſe could be, unleſſe to retard and hinder all good Laws; eſpecially conſidering of what metall moſt of your Lords now are: how long doe you think it would have been before an Act againſt Adultery, and Fornication; an Act againſt Swearing, and an Act to make Lords pay their debts, or their Lands to be ſold, ſhould have paſſed them? that upper Houſe was ſo high that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153720:24"/>moſt good motions were ſpent and out of breath, before they could get up to them, and then if perchance they had the good hap to meet with a thinne Houſe (moſt of your Lords having other buſineſſe to mind than the publike) and ſo paſſe; yet then they muſt packe to a King, whoſe Prerogative two to one, would whip them down again, and thus, O you Engliſh men, Bils of publike right and intereſt were ſent like Beggars from Conſtable to Conſtable, and at laſt ſtript, and whipt in a Bridewell for begging, that you might be eaſed and ſet free; you and your Repreſentatives being ſo hampered, that they were forced to beat Hemp many times, whereby cords have been made to ſtrangle your Liberties, and bind your Armes.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Brave Earles and Barons, the <hi>quondam</hi> Protectors of your Liberties, purchaſed their Honors by ſpending their Bloud for their Countryes good, not by money gotten by oppreſſing their Country: they were engaged therefore to ſtand for their Countries good, even to maintaine their own honour, for no way better to maintain it, than the ſame by which they gained it.</p>
            <p>Thoſe generous ſoules were a Terror and Curb to Tyrants, not their Creatures and ſlaviſh inſtruments, as depending upon their own worth, and their Countryes Love, not Kings mere creations: their principles of education led them to endeavour to be Lords over, not Apes unto the <hi>French,</hi> and he was counted the braveſt Lord, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered moſt of their Men, not the fineſt, that followed moſt of their faſhions; ſcarres were the Ornaments of a noble face, not blacke patches; and hair powdered with duſt, and dewed with ſweat, and bloud, not with perfum'd powders and <hi>Geſmin</hi> butter, was the dreſs wherein <hi>Englands</hi> Nobles courted their Miſtreſſe, <hi>Heroick fame;</hi> they deſigned their Hawking and Hunting to enable them in knowledge of paſſages and riding, not themſelvs to be Faulconers and Huntſmen, whereby to learn to ſwear more readily, their Lands were let at eaſie rates, with ſome ſervices reſerved, whereby their Tenants being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men might not be broken ſpirited, and alſo might be obliged to attend them, when their Countryes ſervice called them forth, hence came <hi>Englands</hi> valiant Yeomanrie, and her bold Barons, who by frequent Parliaments knew how to manage great Counſels, perform worthy actions, reſtrain and curbe Tyrannicall Monarchs. Theſe men were rather a Spurre, than bridle to the Commons in all good actions; <hi>proh dolor ni fuerunt at nunc ſpolia ampla Tyranni,</hi> for a diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:153720:25"/>Court, neglect if not diſcountenancing of daring and knowing men with preferring Muck-worms, and low ſoules captivated with gilded follies, hath choaked thoſe Seeds of vertue, and overſpread the Garden with weeds and thiſtles, and when a King will be a Tyrant, his Lords and Courtiers muſt be ſlaves, or the deſign will never cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and it was eaſie to gueſs what a brood of Snakes was like to be by the Suns ſhining on Dunghils.</p>
            <p>But to omit others, there need be no argument brought to confirm this Act, but that which <hi>'Pryn</hi> hath brought againſt it. For let us take for granted, what he hath lately in Print affirmed, <hi>That the King and Lords were the Parliament heretofore,</hi> and ſo I hope by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence had the power of the Sword and Purſe too, and it wil make much for us. For if our Anceſtors upon feeling the inconvenience and miſchief thereof, could take that power of taxing from them, and beſtow it on their own Repreſentatives (for without doubt the major part of them parted not with it of their own accord) then ſure it will follow, that We upon the ſenſe of the like miſchief may take away the reſt, unleſſe it can be ſhewed, that we onely of all Engliſhmen, muſt not have that power which our Anceſtors had, and which is allowed to all Nations and People, by the Law of Nature and Reaſon, both which are the Lawes of God; and which never commanded that a whole Nation ſhould be oppreſſed, to maintain the luſt and riot of a few Drones. <hi>Solomon</hi> bids the ſluggard go learn of the <hi>Ant,</hi> and why may not we of the <hi>Bee,</hi> which will not ſuffer a Drone in the Hive, that perfect Hieroglyphick, natures own model of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Is it not a great ſcandall and ſtain to Religion, to cut off the King, it being contrary to the doctrine of all Proteſtant Churches?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>
               </label> Should a Cavalier put this queſtion, I would anſwer by another; asking whether murder, and aſſaſſination be not contrary to all Chriſtianity or Morallity either? what haſt thou to do then with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſo long as the murders of thy party and their aſſaſſinations are ſo many?</p>
            <p>But if one who is not of that party, or at leaſt hath not been hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, propound it, I ſhall thus reply. For a private perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to deſtroy and murder their Kiing, or lawfull Magiſtrate, on pretence of Religion, he being a Papiſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is diſclaimed by Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and this to ſhew their diſſent from the Ieſuited Papiſts, who
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153720:25"/>maintaine it lawfull, nay meritorious to kill a Magiſtrate, who is an Heretick, that is no ſlave to <hi>Rome,</hi> but for a Parliament and State to call a Tyrant to account, is not: This Doctor <hi>Willet,</hi> and <hi>Paraeus</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that place in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans, be ſubject to the higher powérs, &amp;c.</hi> hold lawfull; and it is confirmed by a multitude of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Divines, and reaſons, as you may ſee at large in a late treatiſe, entituled, <hi>The tenor of Kings and Magiſtrates.</hi> This King <hi>James</hi> aſſerts, <hi>Buchanan</hi> maintains lawfull, and the Proteſtants in <hi>Scotland</hi> practiſed againſt the late Kings Grand-mother, whom they not only depoſed, but would have beheaded had ſhe not fled, for crimes which bore no proportion with her Grand-ſons, who had not only broke his Oath, and forfeited his Crown, but out-lawed himſelfe by appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from the Law, and the Iudges of Law, the Supreme Court, to the Sword; For the moſt perverſe cannot deny it a full and free Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when he firſt plotted, and after raiſed Arms againſt it: What a ridiculous thing then is it in <hi>Pryn</hi> to bring in his old muſtie Records, and caſes in Law, for defence of Him and his title, nay what a deridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous thing is it in Him, to go about to overthrow all his former works, with that poor ſhift, that they were Popiſh Parliaments, but what if they were? they had not that power as they were Popiſh, but as they were Parliaments, yea <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliaments, not as Papiſts, but as men, yea <hi>Engliſh men;</hi> and ſure our Parliament and we are ſo, for undoubtedly the Proteſtant Religion, hath not deſtroyed Gods image in us, and made us Brutes or Slaves.</p>
            <p>And now Gentlemen, I hope you will diſcern, that the Army hath not only acted according to thoſe Principles, upon which they and we firſt engaged, to wit, That the King was not above Law, That the Parliament was the ſupreme power, and not onely maker, but judge of Law, all declared by this Parliament, and aſſerted by <hi>Pryn;</hi> but according to the principles of Reaſon, and that univerſall, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and unalterable Law of common-ſafety. That the preſent, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Army have diſcharged their truſt, vindicated the power of Parliaments, the Nations liberty, and that cauſe wherein all the wel-affected, and religious were engaged; which had they not done, what a cry of innocent bloud had aſcended up againſt them, how mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable had we been, and in what a ſlaviſh condition?</p>
            <p>Conſider whether we had not been, had they don as the reſt of the, ſecluded Members, in the ſame condition our Anceſtors were in the the time of <hi>Richard</hi> 2. when in a Parliament 19th year of him, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153720:26"/>to <hi>Shrewſbury,</hi> the Major part of Lords, wrought upon by the King, and of the Commons, by <hi>Buſhie</hi> the Speaker, looking onely upon the Kings Intereſt, deſerted the Common-weale, then followed the blank Charters, and thoſe other horrid extortions, which you may read and weep over in the Chronicles, and then ſuffered thoſe Lords and Gentlemen, who had ſtood faithfull to their Countrey.</p>
            <p>Thus might we have ſeen thoſe, and worſe cruelties, not only acted againſt our Civill Liberties, but our Religion alſo, and have lamented and wrung our hands over the Graves of thoſe Worthies, whom he had ſeen betrayed to the unmerciful Sword of an enraged Tyrant, yea and cried out of and curſt both Parliament and Armies treachery whoſe faithfullneſſe now we ſo exclaime againſt.</p>
            <p>And now having briefly runne through theſe, give me leave to ſpeake a word or two to ſome ſcruples, caſt into the ballance to make this Common-wealth ſeeme wanting in its juſt weight.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> And firſt it is objected; <hi>That this is rather a Military Tyrannie ſet up, and maintained by the Sword, than a juſt and lawfull power, and therefore in Conſcience it cannot be obeyed, though in things indifferent, nay lawfull and neceſſary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>
               </label> 1. To this firſt I ſhall thus reply, That if this may be pleaded, all Governments in their beginnings might be denyed, which have all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes been thus eſtabliſhed, and the Sword committed to the publike Miniſters, or Miniſters of State, to cut off all who ſhall goe about to overthrow the Government; if this Plea therefore be admitted, no Government could lawfully have been obeyed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in our caſe, it was impoſſible for any man to have expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any other, for if either part prevail'd, it muſt be by the Sword, that being once appealed unto; eſpecially if we conſider the malice and trechery of the Enemy, which would ſuffer no ſafety, longer than they could be kept at the Swords point: how unhandſomely then can ſuch an exception come from thoſe, who with might and maine called upon the people to come in to aide the Parliament; yea, and enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them by Covenant, to endeavour with their lives and fortunes, a Reformation. Suppoſe the King had agreed to the Propoſitions, and been ſet up to hawk, hunt, bowle, and play at Tennis, whilſt the Parliament managed the great and publike affairs, had not this been by the Sword, which not only captivated his Body, but forced his minde to yeeld to part with thoſe things, which he eſteemed above
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:153720:26"/>the bloud of ſo many thouſands, yea his very owne? what would the power of the Militia have been in the Parliaments diſpoſing, other than a maintaining the Government by the Sword? ſurely then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that intereſt is not ſet up, which theſe men would have, only cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes this objection, whoſe baſis is founded upon impoſſibility, whereupon none can build, but ſuch as erect Caſtles in the air.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Again that it is the higheſt imprudency for any to ſurmiſe that the Parliament, when they had beaten the Enemy in the field, ſhould preſently caſhiere their Forces, for beſides the reſtleſſeneſſe of the Enemy with their parties in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> they were Natives, not driven out, but only diſarmed, who not only lived among us, and ſo at hand, but were ſo falſe, that no tie could hold them from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring our, and our cauſes ruine; how many after compoſitions made, and oathes taken never to bear armes againſt the Parliament, have broken both? unleſſe therefore they would have an Enemy, firſt be exaſperated, and then us to lay our throats bare to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengefull rage, they muſt be aſhamed of this objection, which the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond war is enough to confute, where the Parliament cauſe had been utterly deſtroyed, had it not been for the Army.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, let one of theſe Objectors tell me, why a Reformation gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and maintained by the Sword in <hi>England,</hi> is ſo unlawfull, which in other places is ſo juſt and pious? Theſe Objectors themſelves would account that man a Papiſt, or Popiſhly affected, who ſhould thus reproach the Proteſtants in <hi>Bohemia, Germany, Switzerland, France,</hi> the <hi>Vnited Prrvinces,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> yet did theſe maintaine their Religion, and gain their Liberties by the Sword, by this the <hi>Switzers</hi> cantoniz'd themſelves, and the <hi>Dutch</hi> became a Free-ſtate; by this the Proteſtant Religion was defended, and the Presbyterian Government firſt ſetled in <hi>Scotland,</hi> their Queen being depoſed, and forced to ſue to ſave her Head, for oppoſing it: and by this the Kirk now again repaired, when Epiſcopacy and Popery had well neare le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd Her: Laſtly by this the <hi>Hamiltonian</hi> Parliament was expell'd, and the preſent Rulers ſet up in <hi>Scotland;</hi> For it was the Sword of our Army ſet them in the Saddle, and the Sword of their Army that kept them in it, which for this purpoſe hath been ſo often purged and re-purged by the Kirks importunity, to maintein her againſt all her Maligners; ſure then though the Sea may alter the caſe in the reſt, yet methinkes a ſmall River cannot make ſuch a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:153720:27"/>but that the ſame actions may be warranted by the ſame reaſon.</p>
            <p>And now having been bold to paſſe <hi>Tweed;</hi> I meet with another Objection.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That the ſending the Army of</hi> England <hi>into</hi> Scotland, <hi>is a breach of the large Treaty and Covenant; and againſt the rules of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to Invade our Neighbours thus by an offenſive War.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>
               </label> Though the Scots invading us, taketh off the firſt Charge, untill it be proved, <hi>That</hi> Scotland <hi>had liberty to break, and</hi> England <hi>ſtill to remain bound;</hi> and the Parliaments and Armies Declarations, have not only ſhewed the equity, but neceſſity of thus doing, for this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths mere defence; yet for to ſtop foul mouths, I ſhall adde ſomething.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Parliament could not diſcharge their Truſt to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, ſhould they ſit ſtill and look on untill the Scots, ſtrengthened with forein aids, and home-bred conſpiracies and inſurrections, might break again in upon us, robbing, ſpoyling, raviſhing, and murdering according to their old wont. Our Merchants in the mean while be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing robbed, our Agents aſſaſſinated, and the Trade of <hi>England</hi> ruin'd by the Scots Kings inſtruments, which are boulſtered out by the Scots complying with him, and promiſing his reſtauration, many foreiners winking at them, becauſe doubtfull of our ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What thoughts could forein Princes and States have of the Parliament, ſhould they ſee them maintaining a ſtanding Army at a vaſt charge in <hi>England,</hi> onely to wait untill the Scots pleaſe to come and invade us, which beſides the charge, to the undoing the ſo late Scot-plunderd Northern Counties, muſt weaken their repute abroad, as not daring to look upon the Scots, untill they ſhall pleaſe to force them to it?</p>
            <p>Nay would not they be accounted men of little courage, and leſſe underſtanding, to ſuffer the Scots to increaſe their ſtrength, reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and proviſions from abroad, and not now endeavour to prevent them, when their friends in <hi>France</hi> are not in a capacity to ayde them, nor their Kings Pyraticall Cozen, with his revolted robbers in a poſſibility to prey for them, and when indeed the nipping this Scotch deſigne in the bud, will be the only means to perſwade <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall,</hi> and other Neighbours, to uſe us more civilly.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But it may be replyed, <hi>That the</hi> Scots <hi>intended us no hurt, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:153720:27"/>would be quiet, if ſo be we would let them alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> That the Scots intended to Invade us, is as clear as that the Sunne ſhineth at Noon-day, they having not only proudly engaged to ſeat their King in the Thrones of the other two Nations, but already ſauci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proclaimed Him <hi>King of Great Britain, and Ireland;</hi> as if the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Eſtates, and Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> had a power of making Kings over, and giving Laws to other Nations.</p>
            <p>May not thoſe they term Sectaries juſtly ſuſpect them guilty of an Antichriſtian ſpirit now, when they arrogate that power to themſelvs which none but the Pope (by all Proteſtants agreed to be the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, the Man of Sinne) uſurped, except the Devill, whoſe carriage to our Saviour was not much unlike theirs to their King, both ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Kingdoms of the Earth, and the glory of them, and ſaying, <hi>all theſe will we give thee, if thou wilt fall down and worſhip us?</hi> yet let them take heed leſt they be found lyars, like him (Crownes and Scepters being onely in Gods diſpoſing, who telleth us, that it is he gives Nations Kings in his wrath) though their King be not able to withſtand the Temptation, <hi>Montroſſe</hi> and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated, and no apparent hope of any ſupplies, from his moſt Bleſſed Father the Pope, whom he hath by his Agent, ſo dutifully asked bleſſing, as yet appearing.</p>
            <p>But though theſe Reaſons ſhould be thought inſufficient, yet now God hath made their intent manifeſt by <hi>Londonns</hi> Letters, by which it appears that they had not only a deſigne to invade us, but expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, if not aſſurances of a party here which would ſecond them.</p>
            <p>And now the Scots have thus done, and the premiſes conſidered, what ſhadow of reaſon appears to the contrary, but that we for our own defence, may ſerve them as they did us, and enter <hi>Scotland</hi> with our Army, as they did <hi>England</hi> with theirs, a little before this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment begun? that they were invited in by any in Authority, is falſe; it may be they had private well-wiſhers, and ſo no doubt have we now of the Godly party among them, which when the cloud is paſt, which now hangs over them, will appear.</p>
            <p>But now before I conclude, I ſhall crave leave to ſpeak a word or two, and that:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt to the Scots, whoſe Committee of Eſtates and Kirk, I would intreat to be ſo farre Chriſtians, as to pull the beam out of their own eyes before they meddle with the mote in ours, and ſo much men as
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:153720:28"/>to act and ſpeak rationally, and not to call the ſame action in us an offenſive War, which in them was a defenſive one. Laſtly, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riddle this <hi>Aenigma,</hi> How <hi>Montroſſe</hi> could be a Traytor for but acting according to their Kings Commiſſion, and Command, and yet their King none? it is a rule in reaſon <hi>quod efficit tale illud eſt magis tale,</hi> that which makes a thing to be ſuch, that is more ſuch it ſelfe: and it is affirmed in Scripture, <hi>That God is no reſpecter of perſons, but that the ſoule that ſinnes ſhall dye;</hi> and ſhould not the Gods on earth to whom the Sword of Iuſtice is committed, be ſo too? That maxime, <hi>That the Crown takes off all Attainder,</hi> made by time-ſerving Lawyers, cannot be pleaded in this caſe: For the Commiſſion <hi>Montroſſe</hi> acted by, was given him ſince their King was Proclaimed at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and yet <hi>Montroſſe</hi> was by them adjudged as a Traytor and Enemy of his Countrey, which according to this he could not be, he doing only as his and their King commanded, whoſe deeds are free from Attainter by having the Crowne: but if it ſhould paſſe for Law here, yet I am ſure it will be no good plea at the high Tribunall of that juſt God, who reſpected not the Crowns of the <hi>Canaanitiſh</hi> Kings, <hi>Agag,</hi> or of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whom he commanded to be cut off, and not a male of their Seed to live. There could be no peace to <hi>Ioram,</hi> ſo long as the whoredomes of his Mother <hi>Jezabel</hi> and her witchcrafts were ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and this command the Elders of <hi>Jezrell</hi> who durſt ſtone <hi>Naboth,</hi> durſt not reſiſt, when they perceived that evill from the Lord was gon out againſt <hi>Ahabs</hi> Houſe: and it is not ſo cleer, but that it may be doubted, whether God have not a controverſie with their Kings fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, againſt which, to omit the Idolatries, and other groſſe ſinnes, the innocent bloud of ſo many Martyrs, both for Religion and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, cryes for vengeance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To the Presbyterian party in <hi>England,</hi> whom I deſire to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, That though the preſent ruling power and Kirk in <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſhould have no by-defignes, yet how they may not be able to help to deliver them from the fury of the Malignant party of Lords, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who have twice allready overreached them, in the late Invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>England,</hi> and later in <hi>Ireland,</hi> where after they had made uſe of the Presbyters to gain the Scots in <hi>Vlſter</hi> to their party, they abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed them, forced ſome to flye for their lives, and openly proclaimed it death to any, <hi>who ſhould but ſpeak of having their King come in upon termes.</hi> Let them beware of Inſurrections at home, when it may be
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:153720:28"/>they may at firſt be made uſe on to begin, as lately in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> but when the deſigne came to the height, be turned off, as thoſe Gentlemen in <hi>Eſſex</hi> were by the Malignant party, inſomuch that Sir <hi>William Hixe</hi> a prime ſtickler and others, becauſe they had been for the Parliament were threatned to be ſtabb'd, and forced to flye.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, to you all who are <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> whom it much concerns; If you will but conſider what miſery a Scotch Invaſion, what ſlavery a Scotch Conqueſt muſt beget. Inquire of the Scots de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanor in their late Invaſion, nay and when they came in with their brotherly aſſiſtance for your ſatisfaction in the firſt; and call but to minde the inſolency of the Scots, and Tyranny of their Kings which came in by Conſent: and it will be evident what muſt be expected, ſhould they come in by Conqueſt; their <hi>Iamie</hi> and they, ſhared then onely the Crowne Lands and Treaſure, with the richeſt publike offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; but their Babie <hi>Charles</hi> and they, will divide your private eſtates, and caſt Lots for your Inheritances: to conclude, call to minde your brave Anceſtors, the leaſt drop of whoſe generous bloud, remaining in your veins, will make you not only abhorre, but ſcorn a vaſſalage to that Nation, whoſe beggary, (to omit its inſolency, naſtineſſe, and lechery) all <hi>Englands</hi> ſo much already exhauſted Treaſure, will not be able to releeve.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153720:29"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153720:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
